(music)
WHERE IS SLEEP?
"OVER THE MOUNTAINS OF THE MOON,
DOWN THE VALLEY OF THE SHADOW,
'NEATH THE WAVES OF THE DEEP GULF STREAM, '
REPLIED THE HANDSOME DUKE
IN DARK,
LANGUID TONES.
(music)
IN DARK...
LANGUID TONES.
DARK, FOREBODING...
FOREBODING TONES.
HE FERVENTLY STROKED HER ALABASTER BROW,
AND SHE FELL UNDER HIS CLOAK OF DARKNESS.
[ Sigh ]
(music)
[| Quiet chatter |]
MORGAN, LOOK.
DO YOU THINK SHE NEEDS HELP?
(music)
ARE YOU A...
A JOURNALIST?
NO, A TEACHER.
NO!/M A WRITER.
ACTUALLY | WRITE BOOKS.
OH. BOOKS.
BOOKS.
| HOPE NOTHING'S SPOILED, OR MISSING.
DOESN'T MATTER. | KEEP IT ALL FILED AWAY
IN MY IMAGI-NATION ANYWAY.
MORGAN.
MORGAN, WE'LL BE LATE FOR OUR LUNCHEON.
THANK YOU.
EXCUSE ME.
(music)
Children: (singing) NO MORE PENCILS, NO MORE BOOKS, (singing)
(singing) NO MORE TEACHER'S DIRTY LOOKS (singing)
| Mixed chatter |.
BYE, BARBARA SHAW.
DON'T FORGET YOUR LUNCH PAIL.
Girl: BYE, SHIRLEY. BYE.
BYE, JACOB.
GOOD LUCK IN YOUR JOB AT THE SMITHY.
Children: GOODBYE, MISS SHIRLEY.
! GOODBYE, MISS SHIRLEY. BYE-BYE.
GOODBYE, MISS SHIRLEY, SEE YOU NEXT YEAR.
GOODBYE, MISS SHIRLEY. GOODBYE, MINNIE MAY.
GOOD BYE, MISS SHIRLEY.
[ Sigh ]
IS THAT HOW YOU SMOKE IT?
DON'T YOU KNOW ANYTHING?
YOU GOTTA LICK IT TO MAKE THE PAPER STICK.
[ Blowing raspberry |.
WHAT DO YOU WANT?
MY MAMA SAYS SMOKING MAKES YOUR MOUTH BROWN
AND YOUR EARS STICK OUT.
YOUR MOTHER'S AN OLD WINDBAG.
NO SHE IS NOT.
I'M GOING TO TELL MISS SHIRLEY YOU TWO HAVE BEEN SMOKING.
YOU DO AND ILL LOCK YOU UP AND SIC MY DOG ON YOU.
WILL NOT. YOU CAN'T CATCH ME.
[ Blowing raspberry |.
HELP! LET'S SEE HOW YOU LIKE BEING LOCKED UP,
YOU LITTLE TATTLETALE.
LET ME GO! LET ME GO!
I'M GONNA TELL ON YOU TWO.
LET ME GO. I'M GONNA TELL ON YOU TWO.
YOU TWO ARE BAD BOYS. I'M GONNA TELL...
SEE HOW YOU LIKE THAT, YOU LITTLE TATTLETALE.
YEAH, AND WE'RE GONNA SIC HIS DOG ON YOU
IF YOU SAY ANYTHING.
[ Banging on door | HELP!
[ Sigh ]
[ Banging on door |.
Minnie May: [ Wailing |
| WANT OUT! [ Sobbing ]
WHY, MINNIE MAY!
ANTHONY PYE AND TOMMY BELL LOCKED ME IN
'CAUSE I WAS GOING TO TELL ON THOSE TWO.
THEY WERE SMOKING CIGARETTES.
AND ANTHONY'S GONNA SIC HIS WATCHDOG ON ME.
HE'LL DO NO SUCH THING.
NOW YOU RUN ALONG. YOUR MOTHER WILL BE WONDERING WHERE YOU ARE.
ALL RIGHT, MISS SHIRLEY.
[ Twittering of birds |.
OH, GOOD DAY, MISS SHIRLEY.
GOOD AFTERNOON, MR. PYE.
MUST BE GLAD SCHOOLS OUT.
| HOPE MY ANTHONY BEHAVED HIMSELF THIS YEAR.
ANTHONY'S GRADES HAVE BEEN QUITE GOOD.
AND HE IS WELL-LIKED BY EVERYONE.
| UNDERSTAND FROM MINNIE MAY BARRY,
YOU HAVE AN EXCELLENT WATCHDOG LOOKING OUT FOR YOU, ANTHONY.
OH, AND THAT'S A FACT.
NO FOXES AROUND OUR CHICKEN COOP THIS YEAR, MISS SHIRLEY.
[ Chuckle ] A FINER WATCHDOG YOU'LL NEVER SEE.
SO MINNIE MAY WAS JUST TELLING ME.
OH, AND THANK YOU, ANTHONY, FOR VOLUN-TEERING WITH TOMMY
TO WHITEWASH THE OQUTHOUSE FOR ME NEXT MONDAY.
| HEAR YOU TWO ARE EXCELLENT PAINTERS.
"LL BE SEEING YOU THEN, MONDAY MORNING AT 9:00 O'CLOCK."
GOOD DAY.
YOU'RE OFFO DO SOME PAINTING THEN, ANTHONY, ARE YOU?
(music)
/M SORRY. | KNOW YOU'RE CLOSED, MRS. HARRISON,
BUT | PROMISED MARILLA I'D PICK UP THE MAIL IN TOWN TODAY.
THE POSTMAN, HE LEFT A REGISTERED CARD IN OUR BOX YESTERDAY.
LUCKY YOU CAUGHT US, ANNE SHIRLEY.
DON'T KNOW IF "VE SEEN ANYTHING COME THROUGH TODAY THOUGH."
NO. NO, MA'AM, NOTHING FOR GREEN GABLES.
BUT | HAVE A REGISTERED CARD, MRS. SLOANE.
OH. JUSTA MINUTE NOW.
OH, THAT'S RIGHT.
| REMEMBER ONE OF THEM BIG MANILA ENVELOPES
THAT YOU'VE BEEN SENDING OUT RECENTLY
DID COME BACK YESTERDAY,
REGISTERED MAIL.
THAT IS RIGHT. LET'S SEE.
RIGHT! YES, HERE IT IS HERE. NOW...
CAN'T SEE A THING THOUT MY GLASSES.
GOT YOUR NAME ON IT ALL RIGHT.
CURTIS PUBLISHING COMPANY, BOSTON.
AIN'T THEY MAGAZINE PEOPLE?
MUST BE A COMPLIMENTARY SUBSCRIPTION OR SOME SUCH NUISANCE.
THANKS SO MUCH FOR LETTING ME IN.
GOOD AFTERNOON, MRS. HARRISON, MRS. SLOANE.
[ Jingling of door bell ]
[ Running footsteps |.
SO! AH!
THIS IS WHY YOU KEEP DISAP-PEARING ON ME
EVERY TIME | PLAN TO PICK YOU UP AFTER SCHOOL.
GILBERT BLYTHE!
ALL THIS SECRECY.
YOU NEVER HAVE TIME TO SPEAK TO YOUR FRIENDS ANY MORE.
OH, YOU GIVE THAT BACK OR | WON'T SPEAK TO YOU AGAIN.
WELL, IF YOU'RE GOING TO BE SO TOUCHY.
THANK YOU.
YOU KNOW, PEOPLE THINK YOU'VE BEEN ACTING VERY PECULIARLY LATELY,
AND | MIGHT AS WELL TELL YOU SO.
WHY DIDN'T YOU SHOW UP AT THE CARMODY SPRING FESTIVAL?
| SAVED A SPOT FOR YOU AT OUR TABLE.
| WAS BUSY. | WAS TRYING TO GET MY FINALS MARKED.
ANNE, YOU HAD YOUR FINALS MARKED AND POED WITH THE BOARD BEFORE | DID.
WHAT ARE YOU UP TO?
NOTHING!
THIS IS A COMPLETE-LY PERSONAL MATTER.
| SUPPOSE IT MUST BE IF YOU CAN'T KEEP YOUR WORD ANY MORE.
GOOD GRIEF!
YOU KNOW HOW TO TRY ONE'S PATIENCE, DON'T YOU?
(music)
Gil: DON'T GET UP ON YOUR HIGH HORSE WITH ME, ANNE SHIRLEY.
| CYCLED ALL THE WAY FROM CARMODY TO TELL YOU SOMETHING
| FOUND OUT ABOUT DIANA BARRY TODAY.
YOU ARE A REAL PILL, GILBERT BLYTHE.
WHAT ABOUT DIANA BARRY?
UH-UH, NOT UNTIL YOU SPILL THE BEANS.
YOU WON'T SAY ANYTHING TO YOUR FOLKS,
OR JANE ANDREWS, OR CHARLIE SLOANE?
ON MY HONOUR.
AND YOU PROMISE YOU WON'T EVER TEASE ME ABOUT THIS?
| WOULDN'T RISK YOUR ANGER.
DEAR MISS SHIRLEY:
WE REGRET TO RETURN THE ENCLOSED MANUSCRIPT, "AVERILS ATONEMENT'",
BUT ARE UNABLE TO ACCEPT IT FOR PUBLICATION.
SINCERELY YOURS,
WOMAN'S HOME JOURNAL MAGAZINE?
YOU KNOW THE STORY | WROTE THIS SPRING?
'M ATTEMPTING TO HAVE IT PUBLISHED.
[ Gasp/chuckle |]
ANNE, THAT'S TREMENDOUS!
[ Ringing of bicycle bell ] LISTEN TO THIS, EVERYBODY,
AVONLEA'S PUBLIC SCHOOL TEACHER,
SOON TO BECOME WORLD FAMOUS CANADIAN AUTHOR...
IT HASN'T HAPPENED YET, YOU FOOL.
AND DON'T YOU DARE TELL ANYONE.
NOW WHAT'S ALL THE FUSS ABOUT DIANA BARRY?
WELL, FROM WHAT | UNDERSTAND,
SHE'S GOING ON AN EXTENDED VACATION THIS SUMMER.
IS THAT ALL?
WHERE IS SHE GOING?
YOU MEAN WITH WHOM IS SHE GOING?
ALL RIGHT. WITH WHOM THEN?
WHAT DIFFERENCE DOES IT MAKE?
FRED WRIGHT OBVI-OUSLY MAKES A LOT OF DIFFERENCE TO HER.
HE'S PROPOSED AND DIANA HAS ACCEPTED.
PROPOSED?
CHARLIE SLOANE FOUND OUT FROM FRED HIMSELF.
ROLY-POLY FRED WRIGHT?
BUT THEY HARDLY KNOW EACH OTHER.
OF ALL THE STUPID, SENTIMENTAL THINGS FOR DIANA TO DO.
| DIDN'T EVEN KNOW IT WAS LIKE THIS.
SHE PROBABLY ONLY ACCEPTED
BECAUSE FRED WAS THE FIRST PERSON TO EVER ASK HER.
DON'T BE SILLY. FRED'S A TERRIFIC FELLOW.
WELL, HE BETTER STEER CLEAR OF ME.
HE HAS NO BUSINESS WALTZING IN,
STEALING MY BEST FRIEND.
YOU'RE NOT JEALOUS, ARE YOU?
NO.
JUST DISAPPOINTED.
WHY DO PEOPLE HAVE TO GROW UP...
AND MARRY... CHANGE.
OH, YOU'D CHANGE.
IF SOMEONE EVER ADMITTED THAT THEY WERE HEAD OVER HEELS FOR YOU,
YOU'D BE SWEPT OFF YOUR FEET IN A MOMENT.
| WOULD NOT.
AND | DEFY ANYONE WHO WOULD TRY AND MAKE ME CHANGE.
YOU DO?
(music)
LAST ONE TO THE BRIDGE IS A STUFFED GOOSE.
[ Chuckling ]
CHEATERS NEVER PROSPER, ANNE SHIRLEY.
(music)
[ Barking of dog |] Boy: WATCH OUT, ROVER.
Gil: WHOO!
YOU'VE GOT IT NOW, MISS SHIRLEY.
Anne/Gil: [ Laughing ]
[ Clearing of throats ]
Anne: OH, I'M SORRY, DIANA.
SORRY, UM...
BUT GIL, HE'S...
HE FELL IN THE BROOK AND...
WELL, THANK YOU FOR THE LOVELY WALK, DIANA.
Diana: OH, PLEASE THANK YOUR MOTHER FOR THE CROCHETS.
MYRA GILLIS HAD SHE GOT MARRIED,
AND I-'M DETERMINED TO HAVE AT LEAST AS MANY AS SHE HAD.
| SUPPOSED IT WOULD BE IMPOSSIBLE
TO KEEP HOUSE WITH ONLY 36 DOILIES.
BUT | ASSURE YOU, MR. WRIGHT,
DIANA WILL BE THE SWEETEST LITTLE HOMEMAKER IN THE WORLD,
SO LONG AS YOU CAN AFFORD TO LET HER KEEP UP WITH THE GILLISES.
WELL, | HOPE SO.
UH, GOOD DAY, LADIES. GILBERT.
WELL, | BETTER GO GET MY BICYCLE.
"'LLALK TO YOU LADIES LATER."
BYE.
[ Sigh ] ANNE SHIRLEY...
THAT WAS...
"VE NEVER BEEN SO HUMIL-IATED IN ALL MY LIFE."
THAT WAS THE MEANEST...
HOW COULD YOU MAKE FUN OF MEIN PUBLIC?
DIANA...
| WASN'T MAKING FUN.
| WAS JUST TEASING.
/M SORRY.
YOU ALWAYS HAVE TO BE THE CENTRE OF ATTENTION
WHENEVER GILBERT BLYTHE IS IN ANYONE'S COMPANY.
THAT'S NOT TRUE.
PLEASE FORGIVE ME, DIANA.
| DIDN'T MEAN TO PICK A QUARREL.
[ Sigh ]
WHY COULDN'T YOU HAVE TOLD ME ABOUT YOU AND FRED YOURSELF?
[ Sob/sniffle | | FEEL LIKE I'VE LOST MY BEST FRIEND.
YOU WERE... YOU WERE SO BUSY,
WRITING YOUX BOOK AND MARKING EXAM PAPERS.
IT JUST HAPPENED.
[ Sniffling |.
AND HE ASKED ME...
[ Laugh |]
I'M REALLY HAPPY.
BUT IT DOES SEEM RIDICULOUS
TO THINK OF ME BEING ENGAGED TO FRED, DOESN'T IT?
OH, | DON'T CARE WHAT HE LOOKS LIKE.
HE... HE'S GOT A GOOD HEART.
HE'S SO THOUGHTFUL.
WE'LL PROBABLY MAKE A PUDGY OLD COUPLE SOME DAY,
BUT IT DOESN'T MATTER.
| AM GLAD FOR YOU, DIANA.
DON'T YOU EVER MEAN TO GET MARRIED?
PERHAPS, IF | MEET THE RIGHT ONE.
WHAT ABOUT GILBERT?
GILBERT'S JUST A CHUM.
| DON'T CARE FOR HIM IN THAT WAY.
YOU KNOW WHAT MY IDEAL IS, DIANA.
TALL, IRRESISTIBLY HANDSOME,
PROUD AND MELANCHOLIC.
BUT PEOPLE'S IDEALS CHANGE SOMETIMES.
MINE WOULDN'T.
| WOULDN'T CARE FOR ANY MAN WHO DIDN'T FULFIL THEM.
WHAT IF YOU NEVER MEET HIM?
WELL, THEN | SHALL DIE AN OLD MAID.
OH, | SUPPOSE YOU'RE RIGHT TO BE DISCRIMINATING.
HALF THE MEN ACROSS THE COUNTRY WILL BE COURTING YOU
WHEN YOUR STORY IS PUBLISHED.
YOU'RE GOING TO BE FAMOUS, AND I'LL BE SO PUD.
WHAT IS IT?
OH...
"WOMAN'S HOME JOURNAL" SENT IT BACK.
WHAT?
WELL, THEIR EDITOR MUST BE CRAZY.
WHAT REASON DID HE GIVE?
NO REASON AT ALL, JUST A PRINTED SLIP
SAYING IT WASN'T ACCEPTABLE.
THAT'S RIDICULOUS! THEY MUSTN'T HAVE READ IT.
I'M GOING TO CANCEL MY SUBSCRIPTION IMMEDIATELY.
"AVERILS ATONEMENT~"
IT SOUNDED SO INSPIRING AND ROMANTIC.
BUT YOU CAN TELL ME TRUTHFULLY, DIANA,
IF YOU RECALL ANY MAJOR FAULTS IN MY STORY.
[ Sigh ] WELL...
T-THE PART WHERE... WHERE AVERIL MAKES THE CAKE...
DOESN'T... IT DOESN'T SEEM TO MATCH THE REST OF THE STORY.
THAT'S ONE OF THE MOST ROMANTIC PARTS IN THE WHOLE STORY.
IT'S A WELL-KNOWN FACT THAT GREAT LADIES OF OLD BELIEVED
THAT THE CULINARY ARTS ALSO FED THE SOUL.
WELL, I'LL HAVE TO READ IT AGAIN
TO REMEMBER WHAT MY FIRST OPINION WAS.
IF YOU LET ME KEEP IT, MAYBE | CAN SUGGEST SOME CHANGES.
YOU DON'T KNOW HOW DISCOURAGING ITISTOGETA REJECTION, DIANA.
AND RIGHT WHEN MIN THE MIDST OF WRITING A NEW EPIC:
"" ROSAMUND'S REVENGE.'
THIS CERTAINLY TAKES THE BLOOM OFF THE ROSE.
[awling of cow ]
DON'T BE DISCOURAGED. ANNE SHIRLEY!
I'M NOT GOING TO PUT UP WITH THIS A DAY LONGER.
| WARNED MARILLA NOT TO LET IT HAPPEN AGAIN.
WELL, IT HAS.
PATIENCE HAS CEASED TO BE A VIRTUE.
|WANT THIS RUMPUS STOPPED RIGHT NOW.
IF YOU COULD JUST CALM DOWN AND TELL ME WHAT THE TROUBLE IS.
HAH! CALM DOWN.
FIRST IT WAS OUR POTATOES. THEN MY JUNE LILIES,
WHICH THOMAS PLANTED ON OUR 25th WEDDING ANNIVERSARY.
NOW THIS DARN JERSEY COW HAS DEVOURED ALMOST
ALL MY PRIZE-WINNING CABBAGES.
AND IF TILLIE BOULTER WALKS AWAY WITH
THE RED RIBBON AT THE CHARLOTTETOWN EXHIBITION,
YOU CAN LET MARILLA KNOW | AM HOLDING HER FINANCIALLY RESPONSIBLE.
'M SORRY, MRS. LYNDE, BECAUSE DOLLY IS MY COW, NOT MARILLA"S.
MATTHEW BOUGHT HER FOR ME TWO YEARS AGO AS A CALF FROM MR. BELL.
SORRY! WELL, SORRY IS NOT GOING TO HELP THE HAVOC
THIS ANIMAL HAS MADE TRAMPLING THROUGH MY CABBAGES.
AND IF YOU THINK...
| AM SORRY.
BUT THE FENCE THAT SEPARATES YOUR POTATO FIELD
FROM OUR PASTURE IS AN EYESORE.
AND IF YOU KEPT IT INBETTER REPAIR,
DOLLY WOULDN'T HAVE BROKEN IN.
A JAIL FENCE WOULDN'T KEEP THAT DEVIL OUT.
AND WHAT'S MORE, MY THOMAS HAS BEEN FAR TOO ILL THE PAST SIX MONTHS
TO REPAIR ANY FENCES.
AND | KNOW ONE THING, YOU RED-HEADED SNIPPET,
YOU'D BE BETTER EMPLOYED FIXING THAT FENCE YOURSELF
RATHER THAN MOONING AROUND,
WASTING YOUR TIME WRITING FOR SOME RUBBISHY MAGAZINE.
| WOULD RATHER SPEND MY TIME PROFITABLY,
THAN SQUANDER IT IN IDLE GOSSIP
MEDDLING IN OTHER PEOPLE'S AFFAIRS.
OH!
| WON'T CHERISH ANY HARD FEELINGS AGAINST YOU
BECAUSE OF YOUR NARROW-MINDED OPINIONS.
NOTHANK GOODNESS | HAVE AN IMAGINATION
WHICH ALLOWS ME TO UNDERSTAND
HOW IT MUST BE TO FIND A COW AMONGST PRIZE-WINNING CABBAGES.
DOLLY SHALL NEVER BREAK INTO YOUR FIELD AGAIN.
| GIVE YOU MY WORD OF HONOUR
ON THAT POINT. WELL!
YOU JUST MAKE SURE
THAT SHE DOESN'T.
[ Bawling of cow |.
WHOA. WHOA, WHOA.
WELL, MARILLA, | HOPE THAT CANAL HORSE DESTROYS YOUR TOMATO PATCH NEXT.
AND DON'T EXPECT ANY SYMPATHY FROM YOUR GIRL.
"VE ALWAYS WARNED YOU SHE HAD A TEMPER TO MATCH HER HAIR."
[Thinking ] OH, GOOD LORD.
[ Clicking of tongue |]
SHE CAN'T POSSIBLY GET OUT NOW
UNLESS SHE TEARS THE FENCE DOWN.
| NEVER REALIZED MRS. LYNDE WAS SUCH A CRANK.
THERE'S CERTAINLY NOTHING OF A KINDRED SPIRIT IN HER.
(music)
YOU SET YOUR HEART TOO MUCH ON FRIVOLOUS THINGS,
AND THEN CRASH DOWN INTO DESPAIR
WHEN YOU DON'T GET THEM. |KNOW.
| CAN'T HELP FLYING UP ON THE WINGS OF ANTICIPATION.
IT'S AS GLORIOUS AS SOARING THROUGH A SUNSET.
ALMOST PAYS FOR THE THUD.
WELL, MAYBE IT DOES,
BUT I'D RATHER WALK CALMLY ALONG,
AND DO WITHOUT BOTH FLYING AND THUD.
[ Ringing of cow bells |.
Anne: MARTIN'S FORGOTTEN THE COWS ON ORCHARD SLOPE.
| WAS AS POLITE AS | COULD BE
UNDER THE CIRCUM-STANCES, MARILLA.
AND | APOLOGIZED,
DESPITE HER STINGING PERSONAL REMARKS.
RACHEL SPECIALIZES IN GETTING UNDER PEOPLE'S SKIN, | KNOW,
BUT YOU OUGHT TO HAVE BIT YOUR TONGUE, ANNE,
SEEING AS WE WERE IN THE WRONG.
NO, |OQUGHT TO HAVE SOLD DOLLY TO GILBERT'S FATHER A MONTH AGO
WHEN HE WANTED TO BUY HER.
| THOUGHT IT WAS JUST AS WELL TO WAIT TILL THE AUCTION,
AND LET ALL THE STOCK GO TOGETHER.
MARTIN, THERE ARE TWO MORE COWS.
RACHEL WILL GET OVER THIS.
HER NERVES HAVE BEEN RAW LATELY, AND DESERVEDLY SO.
THOMAS IS PRETTY BAD, AND DR. SPENCER SAYS
THAT HE WON'T BE WITH US FOR VE LONG.
| HOPE SHE DOESN'T HAVE TO SELL HER FARM.
ITDBEA TERRIBLE LOSS.
AND | KNOW HOW WE FELT WHEN MATTHEW DIED.
ANNE, I'VE WANTED TO TALK TO YOU ABOUT SOMETHING FOR A WHILE.
|IKNOW YOU'VE BEEN CONTENT ENOUGH HERE,
BUT | NEVER FEEL AT EASE,
THINKING ABOUT HOW YOU HAVE GIVEN UP SO MUCH OF YOUR OWN OPPORTUNITY.
MARILLA, | COULDN'T LEAVE YOU ALONE HERE.
BESIDES, I'M... 'D PROBABLY MAKE A MUCH BETTER TEACHER
THAN A WRITER ANY DAY. ANNE...
YOU HAVE BEEN MY COMFORT AND MY JOY
SINCE MATTHEW PASSED AWAY.
BUT | PROMISED MYSELF
WHEN YOU GAVE UP THE AVERY SCHOLARSHIP TO STAY HOME,
'D MAKE IT UP TO YOU ONE DAY.
"VE NEVER BEEN SORRY I'VE STAYED FOR A MOMENT."
MR. BARRY HAS REALLY TAKEN OVER THE FARM ALMOST COMPLETELY AND...
MY EYESIGHT IS SOQ MUCH BETTER NOW,
| CAN MANAGE WITH MARTIN.
PERHAPS ONE OF THE PICARD GIRLS OVER IN RUSTICO
COULD... BOARD WITH ME FOR A WHILE,
SO YOU COULD DUST OFF SOME OF YOUR AMBITIONS IF YOU LIKE.
WHAT DO YOU THINK ABOUT THAT?
OH, MARILLA!
| FEEL AS THOUGH SOMEONE'S HANDED ME THE MOON,
AND | DON'T EXACTLY KNOW WHAT TO DO WITH IT.
MATTHEW AND | SPENT 40 YEARS LOOKING AFTER PAPA.
PERHAPS | NEVER MENTIONED IT BEFORE, BUT...
| CAN'T HELP BUT CONFESS,
IT WAS WITH A REGRETFUL HEART AT TIMES.
YOU HAD A LITTLE BIT OF ROMANCE IN YOUR OWN LIFE, MARILLA.
YOU WOULDN'T THINK IT TO LOOK AT ME, WOULD YOU?
BUT YOU CAN NEVER TELL ABOUT PEOPLE BY THEIR OUTSIDES.
DO YOU SUPPOSE THAT MR. BLYTHE REMEMBERS THAT HE WAS YOUR BEAU?
STUFF AND NONSENSE. [ Giggling ]
NO, NO. THAT'S ENOUGH NOW.
NO MORE FOOLISHNESS.
OH, IT SEEMS SO FUNNY AND HORRIBLE
TO THINK OF DIANA MARRYING FRED, DOESN'T IT?
WHAT IS SO HORRIBLE ABOUT IT?
WELL, HE CERTAINLY ISN'T THE WILD, DASHING YOUNG MAN
DIANA USED TO WANT TO MARRY.
FRED IS...
EXTREMELY GOOD.
THAT IS EXACTLY WHAT HE SHOULD BE.
WOULD YOU WANT TO MARRY A WICKED MAN?
WELL, |WOULDN'T MARRY ANYONE WHO WAS REALLY WICKED.
BUT | THINK I'D LIKE IT IF HE COULD BE WICKED...
AND WOULDN'T.
(music)
YOU'LL HAVE MORE SENSE SOMEDAY, | HOPE.
| BELIEVE ANNE SHIRLEY JUST COPIED THAT STORY.
| AM SURE | REMEMBER READING IT IN A NEWSPAPER YEARS AGO.
WELL, I'M SORRY TO HEAR SHE'S TAKEN TO WRITING NOVELS AT ALL.
NOBODY BORN AND BRED IN AVONLEA WOULD DOIT.
BEEN WRITING ANY MORE STORIES LATELY, MISS SHIRLEY?
NO, MRS. HARRISON.
WELL, NO OFFENSE MEANT.
MABEL SLOANE HERE SAYS SHE FOUND ANOTHER ONE OF THEM BIG MANILA ENVELOPES
COME THROUGH HERE A COUPLE OF WEEKS AGO, THAT'S ALL.
HMM, IT WAS ADDRESSED TO THE
ROLLING RELIABLE BAKING POWDER COMPANY IN MONTREAL.
| SUSPICIONED THAT SOMEBODY WAS TRYING FOR THAT PRIZE
THAT THEY'RE OFFERING FOR THE BEST STORY
INTRODUCING THEIR NEW BAKING POWDER.
THE ADDRESS WASN'T IN YOUR HANDWRITING THOUGH.
| SHOULD HOPE NOT.
I'D NEVER DREAM OF COMPETING FOR ANYTHING SO DISGRACEFUL.
IT WOULD ALMOST BE AS BAD AS JAKE GRIFFITH'S CHATAGHUA SHOW.
BUT THEN THAT'S WHAT COMES OF MARILLA CUTHBERT ADOPTING AN ORPHAN
FROM GOODNESS KNOWS WHERE, OR WHAT KIND OF PARENTS.
OH!
WHY, ANNE, CONGRATULATIONS.
YOU HAVE SUCH A WAY OF PUTTING AVONLEA ON THE MAP.
WELL... THANK YOU.
BUT WHAT DO YOU MEAN?
CONGRATULATIONS FOR WHAT?
[ Sarcastic laugh | YOU WERE ALWAYS SUCH A TERRIBLE FAKE AT MODESTY, ANNE,
EVEN DURING PUBLIC SCHOOL.
WELL, THERE'S NOTHING FAKE ABOUT THE BUSINESS
LAWSON'S GENERAL STORE INTENDS TO DO FROM ALLTHIS.
AND | THINK THAT BLUE YOU'RE WEARING
IS SO DRAMATIC FOR A YOUNG AUTHORESS.
YOU ALMOST LOOK PRETTY INIT.
[ Sarcastic chuckle |.
DON'T SAY THINGS YOU DON'T MEAN, JOSIE.
THAT ANNE SHIRLEY IS SO SMUG.
THAT GIRL ALWAYS DID GIVE HERSELF AIRS.
Boys: CONGRATULATIONS.
CONGRATULATIONS, ANNE.
IT'S AWONDERFUL STORY, ANNE.
CONGRATULATIONS.
WONDERFUL STORY, ANNE.
YOU DESERVE THE BEST.
Women: CONGRATULATIONS. CONGRATULATIONS, MISS SHIRLEY.
CONGRATULATIONS ON YOUR STORY, MISS SHIRLEY.
| REALLY LIKE THE BIT ABOUT THE CAKE.
(music)
GREAT JEHOSOPHAT!
[ Excited murmurs |.
ANNE SHIRLEY, WE'VE BEEN TRYING TO TRACK YOU DOWN EVERYWHERE.
OH, LADIES AND GENTLEMEN, MAY | PRESENT TO YOU
AVONLEA'S FAMOUS AUTHORESS.
FATHER, COME OUT HERE.
OH, MY GOODNESS, MISS SHIRLEY.
| DON'T UNDERSTAND.
YOU WON THE CONTEST, YOU GOOSE.
AND | KNEW YOU'D GO AND DOIT ALL BEHIND OUR BACKS.
Mr. Lawson: QUIET, EVERYBODY, QUIET PLEASE.
[ Clearing of throat ] [ Ringing of cash register bell ]
IT IS MY GREAT PLEASURE
AS OFFICIAL PURVEYOR TO AVONLEA
OF THE ROLLINGS RELIABLE BAKING POWDER COMPANY
TO READ THIS, THE FOLLOWING TRIBUTE.
UH, MISS ANNE SHIRLEY,
GREEN GABLES, PEI.
DEAR MADAM,
WE HAVE MUCH PLEASURE IN INFORMING YOU
THAT YOUR CHARMING STORY, "AVERILS ATONEMENT,"
[ Applause ] HAS WON THE $100 GRAND PRIZE.
INOQUR RECENT COMPETI-TION FOR THE BEST STORY
INTRODUCING THE NAME OF OUR REVERED PRODUCT.
[ Applause ] [ Chuckling ]
UH, THE PRIZE WILL BE PRESENTED BY MR. CHARLES LAWSON
OF LAWSON'S GENERAL, AVONLEA.
WE HAVE ARRANGED PUBLICATION OF THE STORY
IN SEVERAL PROMINENT NEWSPAPERS ACROSS THE COUNTRY,
AND WILL SUPPLY IT INPAMPHLET FORM
FOR DISTRIBUTION AMONG OUR PATRONS.
THANKING YOU FOR THE INTEREST YOU HAVE SHOWN
IN SUPPORTING OUR ENTERPRISES,
WE REMAIN YOURS VERY TRULY
THE ROLLINGS RELIABLE...
BAKING POWDER COMPANY.
YOU'LL SIGN MINE, WON'T YOU? HERE
OH, AND I'M SURE MISS SHIRLEY WILL BE HAPPY
TO SIGN EVERYBODY'S BROCHURES.
AND DON'T FORGET YOUR PURCHASE OF THIS REMARKABLE PRODUCT.
NEXT. ANNE!
OH, /M WILD WITH DELIGHT. AH!
| WAS SURE IT WOULD WIN WHEN | SENT IT INTO THE COMPETITION.
DIANA BARRY! YES | DID.
| THOUGHT OF YOUR STORY IN A MINUTE
WHEN | SAW THE AD IN THE PAPER.
Man: MISS SHIRLEY, WILL YOU SIGN THIS FOR MY DAUGHTER?
[ Mixed hubbub |.
THANK YOU.
WELL | WAS GOING TO TELL YOU TO SEND IT IN YOURSELF,
BUT | FIGURED YOU HAD SO LITTLE FAITH LEFT IN IT, YOU WOULDN'T.
SO | SENT MY COPY.
THEN IF IT HADN'T WON, YOU'D NEVER HAVE KNOWN,
BECAUSE THE STORIES THAT FAILED WEREN'T BEING SENT BACK.
WHY, ANNE, YOU DON'T SEEM A BIT PLEASED.
OF COURSE | COULDN'T BE ANYTHING BUT PLEASED.
IT WAS THE GESTUREOF A TRUE FRIEND
TO TRY TO BOOST MY SPIRITS.
BUT THERE ISN'T A WORD ABOUT...
BAKING POWDER.
OH, | PUT THAT IN. IT WAS EASY AS A WINK.
YOU KNOW THE SCENE WHERE AVERIL MAKES THE CAKE?
WELL, | JUST STATED THAT SHE USED ROLLINGS RELIABLE,
AND THAT'S WHY IT TURNED OUT SO WELL.
SEE? AND THE HERE, IN THE LAST PARAGRAPH
WHERE PERCIVAL CLASPS AVERIL IN HIS ARMS AND SAYS.
"SWEETHEART, THE BEAUTIFUL COMING YEARS"
"WILL BRING US THE FULFILMENT OF OUR HOUSE OF DREAMS."
| ADDED, "IN WHICH WE WILL NEVER USE ANY BAKING POWDER"
"EXCEPT ROLLINGS RELIABLE."
OH-H!
COME ON. | HAVE THE BUGGY. I'LL TAKE YOU HOME.
(music)
YOU'VE WON $100.
AND PRISSY GRANT TOLD ME THAT "CANADIAN WOMEN"
ONLY PAID $5 A STORY.
| CAN'T TAKE IT. IT'S RIGHTFULLY YOURS, DIANA.
YOU SENT THE STORY IN AND MADE THE ALTERATIONS.
| CERTAINLY WOULDN'T HAVE SENT IT.
SO YOU HAVE TO TAKE IT.
I'D LIKE TO SEE MYSELF!
IT WASN'T ANY TROUBLE, ANNE.
THE HONOUR OF BEING THE BEST FRIEND OF THE PRIZE WINNER
IS ENOUGH FOR ME
I'M SO GLAD FOR YOUR SAKE.
| THINK YOU'RE THE SWEETEST AND TRUEST FRIEND
IN THE WORLD, DIANA.
| WILL BUY YOUR WEDDING GIFT WITH THIS.
DON'T YOU DARE SPEND IT ALL ON ME.
| GOT A LETTER TODAY FROM OUR DEAR OLD TEACHER, MISS STACEY.
SHE IS HEAD OF THE KING'S COUNTY BOARD OF EDUCATION IN NEW BRUNSWICK.
WHAT A PROMOTION. WELL, APPARENTLY,
THERE'S A POSITION SHE'S RECOMMENDED ME FOR
AT ALADIES' COLLEGE IN KINGSPORT.
HOW FLATTERING!
YOU WOULDN'T ACTUALLY LEAVE, WOULD YOU?
NO, BUT | OUGHT TO REPLY ANYWAY.
SHE'S GONE TO ALL THIS TROUBLE,
AND | WOULD... [ Bawling of cow |]
STOP, DIANA!
ANNE!
YOU'LL RUIN YOUR DRESS
IN THAT MUDDY FIELD. RUIN IT!
OH, SHE'LL NEVER GET THAT COW OUT BY HERSELF.
(music)
COME BACK!
STOP!
ANNE SHIRLEY, YOU'RE BEING RIDICULOUS.
GET OUT OF THIS FIELD THIS MINUTE.
| DON'T CARE ABOUT MY DRESS.
| MUST GET THE COW OUT BEFORE RACHEL LYNDE SEES HER.
GO ON, DIANA, RUN.
CORNER HER.
THAT'S IT, DIANA.
NOW DON'T FRIGHTEN HER.
THIS IS WHAT WE'VE GOT TO DO.
[ Bawling of cow |.
MAYBE IF WE CAN GET A HOLD OF HER,
WE CAN FORCE HER OVER THE FENCE INTO OUR FIELD.
OKAY, YOU FILL THE GAP,
AND I'M GOING TO MAKE A RUN FORIT,
STRAIGHT TOWARDS HER.
WITH ANY LUCK, SHE'LL JUMP THE FENCE.
YOU DON'T MEAN YOU'RE GOING TO ACTUALLY
WALK THROUGH THAT MULCH, DO YOU?
IT'S THE LESSER OF THE TWO EVILS, DIANA.
WHAT IF SHE WAS GOING TO GET INTO RACHELS CABBAGE PATCH AGAIN?
(music)
ALL RIGHT, | HAVE THE GAP BLOCKED.
COME HERE, DOLLY.
GOOD GIRL.
SHOO. COME ON.
WRETCHED COW.
OH, DON'T EVEN THINK ABOUT RACHELS CABBAGES.
[ Gasp |
[ Shriek ]
COME HERE, YOU STUPID...
Both: [ Yelping ]
[ Whimpering ]
[ Sigh ] SORRY.
Gil: WELL,
THE ELEGANT AND ILLUSTRIOUS MISS SHIRLEY.
UH, RELAXED WHILE SEEKING OUT IDEAS
FOR HER NEXT ROLLING RELIABLE'S...
WRITING ASSIGNMENT, | PRESUME.
WELL, DO YOU SUPPOSE I'M HERE TO CHAT WITH THE BULLFROGS?
BE A GENTLEMAN.
YOU'D HAVE BEEN BETTER OFF SELLING HER LAST MONTH
WHEN DAD OFFERED TO BUY HER.
WELL, I'LL SELL DOLLY TO HIM RIGHT NOW IF HE WANTS HER.
Man: [ Laughing ]
YOU MAY HAVE OUR DARN JERSEY
ANY TIME YOU WANT HER, MR. BLYTHE.
THIS VERY MINUTE FOR THAT MATTER.
[ Laughing heartily | DONE!
LL GIVE YOU THE $20 | OFFERED BEFORE.
GIL CAN DRIVE HER OVER TO CARMODY RIGHT NOW.
SHE'LL GO TO TOWN WITH THE REST OF THE SHIPMENT THIS EVENING.
| PROMISED MR. REED OF BRIGHTON A JERSEY.
[ Chuckling ]
WHAT WILL MARILLA SAY?
SHE WON'T CARE.
DOLLY WAS MY COW ANYWAY.
IT'S NOT LIKELY SHE'LL BRING MORE THAN $20 AT THE AUCTION.
BUT WHEN RACHEL SEES THIS FIELD,
SHE'LL KNOW DOLLY WAS LOOSE.
ANNE, I'LL BE OVER THIS AFTERNOON WITH YOUR $20.
WELL, IT'S TAUGHT ME A LESSON,
NOT TO STAKE MY WORD OF HONOUR ON COWS.
Mr. Blythe: [ Chuckling ]
(music)
HOW DO YOU THINK A MOTHER WOULD FEEL
IF SHE FOUND HER CHILD TATTOOED ALL OVER
WITH A BAKING POWDER ADVERTISEMENT?
| LOVED MY STORY,
AND | WROTE IT OUT OF THE BEST THAT WAS IN ME.
AH, YOU'RE JUST TIRED.
BESIDES, WHY SHOULD YOU CARE?
100 BUCKS IS MORE THAN YOU MAKE IN TWO MONTHS TEACHING ANYWAY.
JOSIE PYE AND TILLIE BOULTER CAN'T WAIT TO POUNCE ON IT.
AH, THEY'RE SPITEFUL OLD CATS.
YOU'RE JUST THE FIRST PERSON IN POKEY OLD AVONLEA
TO TRY ANYTHING LIKE THAT.
ALL PIONEERS ARE CONSIDERED TO BE AFFLICTED WITH MOONSTRUCK MADNESS.
MAD TO THINK | COULD WRITE ANYTHING BETTER
THAN A BAKING POWDER ADVERTISEMENT.
THIS HAS DAMPENED ANY SPARK OF AMBITION.
| SHALL NEVER WRITE ANOTHER STORY AGAIN.
WELL, | WOULDN'T GIVE UP ALTOGETHER.
MAYBE IF YOU JUST LET YOUR CHARACTERS SPEAK EVERYDAY ENGLISH
INSTEAD OF ALL THAT HIGH-FALUTING MUMBO-JUMBO.
YOU THINK MY STORY'S FULL OF FAULTS TOO, DON'T YOU?
"WILT THOU GIVE UP THY GARTER,"
"OH, FAIREST OF THE FAIR?"
ANNE, NOBODY SPEAKS THAT WAY.
AND LOOK AT THAT SAD PERCIVAL
WHO SITS AROUND MOONING THE ENTIRE TIME.
HE NEVER LETS THE GIRL GET A WORD IN EDGEWISE.
IN REAL LIFE, SHE'D HAVE PITCHED HIM.
HIS POETRY WOULD WIN ANY GIRLS HEART.
WELL, IF YOU WANT MY OPINION, MISS SHIRLEY,
I'D WRITE ABOUT PLACES | KNEW SOMETHING OF
AND PEOPLE THAT SPOKE EVERYDAY ENGLISH
INSTEAD OF THESE SILLY SCHOOLGIRL ROMANCES.
| DON'T SHARE YOUR OPINION.
| AM NOT YOUR HORSE, MR. BLYTHE.
| WAS JUST TRYING TO GIVE YOU A BIT OF FRIENDLY ADVICE.
IS THAT SO?
TAKE THE $100,
AND WRITE A REAL STORY ABOUT THE PEOPLE YOU CARE ABOUT,
RIGHT HERE IN AVONLEA.
WELL YOU CERTAINLY WOULDN'T BE ONE OF THEM.
"PITCHING® AND "MOONING"?
[ Sniffle ] YOU KNOW,
YOU'RE ABOUT AS INTELLECTUAL AS CHARLIE,
AND MOODY AND FRED AND ALL THE REST OF THE BOYS
WHO COULD ONLY THINK OF FINDING SOME SILLY GIRL TO MARRY
AND KEEP HOUSE FOR THEM.
WELL, YOU CAN CRY AND FEEL SORRY FOR YOURSELF ALL YOU WANT,
BUT IT WON'T HELP YOU WRITE A BETTEROVEL.
[ Sigh ]
WILL YOU STILL COME TO FRED'S CLAMBAKE WITH ME NEXT TUESDAY?
[ Sniffle ]
LISTEN, ANNE, I'M SORRY.
WILL YOU LET ME WALK YOU BACK?
| WAS JUST TRYING TO BE HELPFUL.
YOU... YOU KNOW YOU GET MY BACK UP SOMETIMES.
LISTEN, I'M SORRY. WHAT ELSE CAN | DO?
[ Grunt of effort ]
LET ME GETA WORD IN EDGEWISE ONCE IN A WHILE,
BEFORE | PITCH YOU!
(music)
WHOA!
GOOD DAY, MARILLA.
WELL... JOHN BLYTHE.
WE HAVEN'T SEEN YOU AROUND THESE PARTS MUCH LATELY.
WELL, | HAVEN'T MUCH TIME FOR SOCIAL CALLS NOWADAYS.
OLD PLACE STILL LOOKS AS PRETTY THOUGH.
THE OLD BUILDINGS ARE GETTING WORN DOWN.
BUT PEOPLE IN AVONLEA STILL SAY
THAT IT'S THE LOVELIEST OLD SPOT ON THE NORTH SHORE.
OH, IT IS THAT.
SOME THINGS NEVER CHANGE EVEN IN 30 YEARS.
I'M LOOKING FOR MY BOY.
YES.
ANNE AND HE ARE WALKING BY THE POND.
MAYBE...
WOULD YOU LIKE TO SIT A WHILE,
TILL THEY COME BACK?
THANKS.
BUT WERE TAKING A SHIPMENT INTO CHARLOTTETOWN BEFORE DARK.
'D BEST GO AND FIND HIM.
[| Whinnying of horse |.
ANNE? WHAT ABOUT YOUR $20?
FOR THE COW.
THE APPLE DOESN'T FALL FAR FROM THE TREE, DOES IT?
GOOD DAY, MARILLA.
(music)
[ Sobbing ] [ Knocking on door |.
THERE, THERE. [ Sniffling |.
YOU TAKE THINGS TOO MUCH TO HEART, ANNE SHIRLEY.
OH, MARILLA,
IT'S BEEN SUCH A JONAH DAY,
WITH ROLLINGS RELIABLE,
AND DOLLY, AND GILBERT.
NOW, NOW, JONAH DAYS COME TO EVERYBODY.
GOD KNOWS BEST.
YOU USED TO SAY...
"TOMORROW IS ALWAYS FRESH WITH NO MISTAKES."
DO YOU REMEMBER?
[ Chuckling ]
OH, WHAT A GIRL YOU WERE
FOR MAKING MISTAKES IN THEM DAYS.
HMMM? [ Gulping |
| USED TO THINK YOU WERE POSSESSED.
DO YOU MIND THE TIME YOU DYED YOUR HAIR?
OH LORD.
OH, WHAT A WORRY MY RED HAIR USED TO BE.
I'M AFRAID I'VE NEVER BEEN ABLE
TO ENDURE PERSONAL CRITICISM VERY WELL.
GILBERT GAVE HIS HONEST OPINION OF MY STORY THIS AFTERNOON.
MY... MY TEMPER... IT ALWAYS GETS THE BETTER OF ME.
| WHIPPED HIM AS HARD AS | COULD.
I'M GLAD TO HEAR IT.
THE BLYTHES HAVE ALWAYS BEEN FAR TOO OPINIONATED
FOR THEIR OWN GOOD.
NO, MARILLA. HE WAS RIGHT.
AND I'VE MADE A TERRIBLE IDIOT OF MYSELF.
YOU DON'T KNOW HOW SPITEFUL | WAS.
| CAN IMAGINE.
OUR FRIENDSHIP... IT WON'T EVER BE THE SAME NOW.
WHY CAN'T HE JUST BE SENSIBLE AND...
INSTEAD OF ACTING LIKE A SENTIMENTAL SCHOOLBOY.
BECAUSE HE LOVES YOU.
HE LOVES ME?
| CAN'T KNOW WHY.
BECAUSE YOU MAKE JOSIE PYE AND RUBY GILLIS
AND ALL OF THOSE WISHY-WASHY YOUNG LADIES WHO'VE WALTZED BY HIM
LOOK LIKE SPINELESS NOTHINGS.
BUT GIL AND I...
HE'S HARDLY MY IDEA OF A ROMANTIC SUITOR.
YOU HAVE TRICKED SOMETHING OUT OF THAT IMAGINATION OF YOURS
THAT YOU CALL ROMANCE.
HAVE YOU FORGOTTEN HOW HE GAVE UP AVONLEA SCHOOL FOR YOU,
SO THAT YOU COULD STAY HERE WITH ME?
HE PICKED YOU UP EVERY DAY IN HIS CARRIAGE,
SO THAT YOU COULD STUDY YOUR COURSES TOGETHER.
DON'T TOSS IT AWAY, ANNE,
FOR SOME RIDICULOUS IDEAL
THAT DOESN'T EXIST.
HMMM?
NOW YOU COME DOWNSTAIRS AND SEE IF AGOOD CUP OF TEA
AND SOME OF THOSE PLUM PUFFS THAT | MADE TODAY DON'T HEARTEN YOU.
PLUM PUFFS WON'T MINISTER TOA MIND DISEASED.
AND A WORLD THAT HAS CRUMBLED INTO PIECES.
WELL, I'M GLAD TO SEE THAT YOUR DENTED SPIRITS
HAVEN'T INJURED YOUR TONGUE.
(music)
SUPPOSE IT'S JUST AS WELL YOU SOLD THE DARN COW...
THOUGH YOU DO DO THINGS IN A DREADFUL HEADLONG FASHION.
| ONLY PRAY THAT RACHEL DOESN'T BURST A BLOOD VESSEL
WHEN SHE SEES HER POTATO FIELDS TODAY.
"VE DECIDED TO WRITE MISS STACEY,
AND ASK HER FOR MORE PARTICULARS ON THIS LADIES' COLLEGE.
| THINK THAT'S A WISE IDEA, ANNE.
GO OUT AND FIND ME A COUPLE OF EGGS, WILL YOU?
| DON'T KNOW HOW IN HEAVEN'S NAME
DOLLY GOT OUT OF THAT PEN.
SHE MUST HAVE JUST BROKEN SOME OF THE BOARDS.
[ Squawking of geese |]
[ Bawling of cow |.
OH NO!
MARILLA, DOLLY'S HERE!
ANNE, WHAT IN HEAVEN'S NAME IS THE MATTER WITH YOU?
WHAT WILL | DO?
OH, THIS IS TERRIBLE AND IT'S ALL MY FAULT.
| MUST LEARN TO REFLECT A LITTLE
BEFORE | GO CHARGING AHEAD RECKLESSLY.
ANNE SHIRLEY, YOU ARE THE MOST EXASPERATING GIRL.
WHAT IS IT THAT YOU'VE DONE?
"VE SOLD RACHEL LYNDE'S JERSEY COW,
THE ONE THEY BOUGHT IN CARMODY LAST SPRING,
TO MR. BLYTHE,
AND DOLLY IS HERE THIS VERY MINUTE IN THE MILKING PEN.
ANNE, ARE YOU DREAMING?
| ONLY WISH | WERE.
THERE'S NO DREAM ABOUT IT,
THOUGH IT'S VERY MUCH LIKE A NIGHTMARE.
THAT IS DOLLY.
RACHEL LYNDE'S COW ISIN CHARLOTTETOWN BY NOW.
MARILLA, | THOUGHT | WAS FINISHED GETTING INTO SCRAPES,
AND HERE | AM IN THE VERY WORST ONE | EVER WAS IN MY ENTIRE LIFE.
WHAT CI DO?
DO? THERE IS NOTHING TO DO
BUT TO GO AND TELL RACHEL THE TRUTH.
YOU ARE JUST GOING TO HAVE TO LEARN TO SETTLE DOWN
AND PAY HEED TO THINGS.
Anne: I'VE HUMILIATED MYSELF.
INTO THE VERY DUST.
MAYBE SHE'D ACCEPT A PLATE OF PLUM PUFFS AS A PEACE OFFERING.
(music)
Anne: OH, NO.
IF SHE'S THAT CROSS, WHAT WILL SHE BE
WHEN | SAY WHAT I'VE DONE?
Marilla: IF SHE GIVES YOU THE CHANCE TO SAY ANYTHING AT ALL.
AFTERNOON, THOMAS.
AFTERNOON, MARILLA.
AFTERNOON, RACHEL. MARILLA.
ANNE. I'M GLAD YOU'VE COME.
| CERTAINLY HAD NO INTENTION OF VISITING YOU PEOPLE
AFTER BEING FLOWN AT AS | WAS ON MY AST VISIT.
WELL, IT WOULD APPEAR THAT SOME KIND OF...
KAFUFFLE HAS COME OUT OF THIS.
ANNE WOULD LIKE TO...
PLEASE, MARILLA,
'M NOT FINISHED YET. ON REFLECTION,
| REALIZED THAT | WAS PARTLY TO BLAME.
| HAD NO RIGHT TO BE SO ILL-TEMPERED WITH YOU,
AND I'M NOT ONE OF THEM THAT CAN NEVER BE BROUGHT
TO OWN UP TO THEIR MISTAKES.
I'D LIKE TO APOLOGIZE TO YOU,
ANNE SHIRLEY,
AND | WONDER IF YOU'D SIGN MY COPY
OF YOUR "AVERILS ATONEMENT"?
THE MONEY THEY PAY FOR SUCH LIES IS PERFECTLY AMAZING, BUT...
| READ IT TO MY THOMAS AND WE WERE BOTH MOVED.
'M MUCH OBLIGED TO YOU,
AS IT'S THE ONLY ENTERTAINMENT HE'S HAD
FOR THE PAST SIX MONTHS.
| LAUGHED SO HARD, 'M NOT SURE IT WASN'T GOOD FOR MY HEART.
'M SO PLEASED.
COME AND LAY OFF YOUR THINGS.
YOU'LL STAY TO TEA, WON'T YOU?
THANK YOU, RACHEL.
Rachel: IT'S NOTHING SHORT OF A WONDER.
HOW YOU'VE IMPROVED, ANNE, IN LOOKS AND TALENT.
I'M NOT OVERLY PARTIAL TO THE PALE, WIDE-EYES STYLE MYSELF.
| PREFER MORE SNAP AND COLOUR.
BUT YOU DO MAKE THEM OTHER AVOLEA GIRLS WITH SHOWY GOOD LOOKS
SEEM KIND OF OVERDONE.
LIKE MY JUNE LILIES ALONGSIDE THEM BIG, RED PEONIES.
THAT'S WHAT.
HERE'S YOUR TEA, THOMAS.
| DON'T WANT ANY TEA.
NOW, THOMAS, YOU JUST FINISH YOUR NAP HERE,
AND GET SOME FRESH AIR.
| REALLY... |WANTED TO CONFESS SOMETHING TO YOU, MRS. LYNDE.
IT'S ABOUT THE JERSEY COW.
| SAW MY TRAMPLED POTATO FIELD THIS MORNING.
NEVER MIND, ANNE. IT MAKES NO DIFFERENCE NOW.
IF ONLY IT WERE THAT, MRS. LYNDE.
BUT IT'S 10 TIMES WORSE.
WELL, YOU'RE NEVER SAFE FROM SURPRISE TILL YOU'RE DEAD.
DON'T TELL ME SHE'S DONE IN THE LAST OF MY CABBAGES TOO.
IT'S NOT THE CABBAGES, MRS. LYNDE,
AND ILL TELL YOU EVERYTHING.
BUT PLEASE DON'T INTERRUPT.
IT'S MAKING ME NERVOUS.
Thomas: RACHEL!
THOMAS, YOU'RE SUPPOSED TO BE SNOOZING.
YOU SEE, DIANA AND | CHASED A CERTAIN JERSEY COW
OUT OF YOUR POTATO FIELD YESTERDAY.
WELL, YOU CAN'T IMAGINE WHAT A DIFFICULT TIME WE HAD.
| WAS SO DREADFULLY TIRED AND WET
AND CROSS AFTER IT ALL,
WELL, | SOLD THE COW ON THE SPOT
TO THE BLYTHES FOR $20.
TSK, TSK, | HOPE YOU'RE NOT VEXED WITH HER, MARILLA.
SHE SHOULD HAVE CONSULTED YOU FIRST.
SO LONG AS MY CABBAGES ARE SAFE,
WE'LL JUST PRETEND IT DIDN'T HAPPEN.
Anne: YOU SEE, THIS MORNING,
| FOUND MY DOLLY STILL SHUT UP IN OUR MILKING PEN.
IT WAS YOUR COW...
THAT ANNE SOLD TO JOHN BLYTHE, RACHEL.
AND IT WAS SHIPPED OUT RIGHT AWAY
ON THE AFTERNOON TRAIN BY MR. BLYTHE.
Marilla: YOU'LL FIND THAT OUR JERSEY IS AS GOOD AS YOURS,
OR PERHAPS YOU'D PREFER THE $20.
MARILLA CUTHBERT,
WE PAID MORE THAN $50 FOR OUR COW.
AND | HAVE NO INTENTION OF ACCEPTING THAT VARMINT OF YOURS IN EXCHANGE.
YOU HAVE ADMITTED YOU ARE PARTIALLY TO BLAME FOR ALL OF THIS.
ANNE SHIRLEY, YOU ARE TOO HEEDLESS AND IMPULSIVE.
YOU JUST GO ON AND DO WHATEVER COMES INTO YOUR HEAD, THAT'S WHAT.
WELL, IN THIS WORLD YOU PAY FOR YOUR MISTAKES,
AND YOU CAN CERTAINLY AFFORD TO PAY NOW.
WELL, YOU HAVE CERTAINLY MADE A FINE EXHIBITION OF YOURSELF, RACHEL,
FALLING ALL OVER THIS GIRL
BECAUSE SHE'S A SUCCESS.
IT'S PLAIN TO SEE NOW
WHAT YOUR TRUE COLOURS ARE.
Thomas: RACHEL! I'M COMING, THOMAS.
OH, THAT MAN! IF HE'D JUST BRAVE UP
AND EXERT HIS WILL POWER A LITTLE,
HE'D GET BETTER IN NO TIME.
IT'S AWONDER TO ME THAT HE DARED TO GET SICK AT ALL
WITHOUT ASKING HER PERMISSION.
COME ALONG, ANNE.
WE'LL PAY HER HER $50.
Rachel: THOMAS!
THOMAS! [| Moaning |]
OH, DEAR GOD, PLEASE DON'T TAKE HIM.
WHAT IS IT, THOMAS?
WHERE'S HIS MEDICINE, RACHEL?
IT'S IN THE CUPBOARD.
IS THIS IT? YES.
RACHEL?
YES, THOMAS, WHAT IS IT?
WHAT IS IT?
| CAN'T HEAR YOU.
OH, THOMAS!
[ Sobbing ]
OH, RACHEL...
I'M AFRAID THERE'S NOTHING WE CAN DO.
[ Sobbing ]
Rachel: THERE WON'T BE MUCH LEFT.
AFTER ALL OUR DEBTS ARE SETTLED.
| EXPECT I'LL GO WEST TO MY ROBERT,
IF HE'LL HAVE ME.
[ Sniffle ]
THE FARM IS MORTGAGED AND...
NOW IT WILL HAVE TO BE SOLD.
NOW, RACHEL.
PULL YOURSELF TOGETHER.
WELL, M NO JELLYFISH. BUT...
A WOMAN MY AGE DOESN'T MAKE FRIENDS AND INTERESTS EASILY, THAT'S ALL.
IT BREAKS MY HEART TO THINK OF LEAVING AVONLEA.
HOW ARE YOU FEELING TIGHT, RACHEL?
A LITTLE BETTER | THINK, THANK YOU, ANNE.
HERE'S MY GIFT, PAID FOR OUT OF THE PROCEEDS OF THE JERSEY COW.
IT'S NOT MUCH OF A PARTY GIFT, BUT...
YOU TELL THEM THAT | PLAN TO GIVE THEM MY ZIGZAG QUILT
AS AWEDDING PRESENT.
WHY, ANNE, YOU HAVEN'T WORN THAT OUTFIT IN AGES.
YOU LOOK LOVELY.
THANK YOU, MARILLA.
GILBERT BLYTHE WILL BE MIGHTY PROUD.
WHY ISN'T HE HERE YET?
PUT ON YOUR SWEATER.
IT'S GOG TO BE COOL THIS EVENING.
'M... PM GOING ALONE, RACHEL.
| HOPE YOU DON'T MIND MY TAKING THE CARRIAGE, MARILLA.
NO. NO.
YOU DID PUT MY NAME ON THE CARD, | HOPE.
OF COURSE, MARILLA.
GOODBYE NOW.
GOODBYE, RACHEL.
HAVE A LOVELY TIME.
BE CAREFUL THAT YOU DON'T GET YOUR SKIRT CAUGHT
IN THE WHEEL OF THE HAY-WAIN, ANNE.
[ Closing of door ]
WELL, MARILLA,
YOU KNOW | PRIDE MYSELF ON SPEAKING MY MIND.
| SMELL TROUBLE, AND | DON'T MIND SAYING SO.
PROVIDENCE MATCHED THEM TWO UP
SINCE THEY WERE CHILDREN, THAT'S WHAT.
AND THEY ARE CHILDREN STILL.
SHE'S 18, AND | WAS MARRIED BY THAT TIME.
BUT ANNE'S GROWN TOO MUCH LIKE YOU, MARILLA.
IT'S THE OVER-PARTICULAR ONES, GET LEFT BEHIN
AND IT IS THE OVER-OPINIONATED THAT END UP UNHAPPY
AND MEANER THAN SECOND SKIMMINGS.
Both: [ Giggling |.
OH! THIS IS GLORIOUS!
DID YOU REMEMBER THE TIME... [ Giggling ]
WE SLEPT ALL NIGHT IN THE HAY LOFT?
AND | WAS SO FRIGHTENED WE WERE GOING TO BE ATTACKED BY THAT BARN OWL,
COME ON, DIANA,
WE'VE GOT TO ORGANIZE THE GIFTS.
DUTY CALLS.
| Fiddle music |.
ANNE, WHERE ARE YOU OFF TO?
WE WON'T LEAVE ANY CLAMS FOR YOU
IF YOU DON'T HURRY BACK.
JUST ENJOYING THE FRESH AIR.
OH, YOU HAVEN'T MET MY FIANCE.
HARRY INGLIS FROM WINNIPEG, ANNE SHIRLEY.
PLEASED TO MEET YOU, MA'AM.
PLEASED TO MEET YOU.
WELL, YOU'RE A VERY LUCKY MAN, MR. INGLIS.
WHERE WILL YOU LIVE?
IN MONTREAL. HARRY'S IN THE MINING BUSINESS.
OH, JANE, STOP SHOWING OFF YOUR RING.
| CAN SEE IT GLIMMERING THROUGH THE TREES.
IT'S BEEN REAL NICE SEEING YOU AGAIN, ANNE.
LET'S GO, HARRY.
YOU BOYS RUN ALONG WITH JANE AND HARRY.
|WANT TO TALK TO ANNE.
ISN'T JANE'S MILLIONAIRE ANCIENT?
HE COULD BE HER FATHER.
WELL, HE CERTAINLY MUST HAVE A LOT OF MOY.
"LL SAY. HE'S JUST SHOWERED HER WITH JEWELLERY."
AND THEY'RE GOING TO EUROPE ON A WEDDING TOUR.
JANE'S SUCH A NICE GIRL.
SHE'S NEVER EVEN TRIED TO ATTRACT ATTENTION.
WELL, SHE'S CERTAINLY NOT IN THE MILLIONAIRE'S CLASS.
WHAT ABOUT YOU, ANNE?
ARE YOU HERE WITH GILBERT?
AREN'T THOSE TWO RIDICULOUS?
THEY'RE DETERMINED TO SIT EACH OTHER OUT.
| REALLY DON'T CARE A SNIT ABOUT EITHER OF THEM, YOU KNOW.
WELL, LET'S GET TOGETHER SOON, ANNE.
| WANT TO HEAR ALL OF YOUR NEWS.
[ Fiddle music ends |
[ Distant applause |
[ Twittering of birds |
[ Fiddle music starts |
| To imaginary partner | ME?
I'D BE HONOURED TO ACCEPT THIS DANCE.
[ Orchestra music |
[ Imaginary conversation |.
WHY THANK YOU.
YOU CAN CALL ME CORDELIA.
CORDELIA, YOU HAVE AN EXQUISITE ROSELEAF COMPLEXION.
DO ALLOW ME.
| HAVE AN ACCOUNT TO SETTLE WITH THIS YOUNG LADY.
YOUR $20.
CARE TO?
[ Orchestra music |
[ Sigh ]
'M SORRY, GIL.
| MUST HAVE TWO LEFT FEET.
WHAT ARE YOU THINKING ABOUT?
I'M AFRAID TO SPEAK OR MOVE
FOR FEAR THAT ALL THIS WONDERFUL BEAUTY WILL JUST VANISH,
LIKE A BROKEN SILENCE.
X DOESN'T IT REMIND YOU OF OUR OLD SCHOOL-DAY PICNICS?
HMMM.
| DON'T WANT ANY OF IT TO CHANGE.
| WISH | COULD JUST HOLD ONTO THOSE DAYS FOREVER.
| HAVE A FEELING THINGS WILL NEVER BE THE SAME AGAIN.
WILL THEY?
[WON'T CHANGE.
THAT'S THE LEAST | CAN PROMISE YOU.
ANNE, THERE'S SOMETHING | WANT TO ASK YOU.
GIL, PLEASE DON'T.
WHAT IS IT?
YOU'VE BEEN AVOIDING ME ALL SPRING, EVER SINCE WE GRADUATED.
| NEVER WANTED TO MAKE YOU CARE FOR ME SO.
| KEPT AWAY SO YOU WOULDN'T.
WELL, | WON'T BE COMING BACK TO WHITE SANDS IN THE FALL.
DALHOUSIE MEDICAL SCHOOL HAS ACCEPTED ME.
GIL, ([M SQ PROUD OF YOU.
I'M SORRY ABOUT LAST WEEK.
| ONLY WANTED TO SHOW YOU HOW MUCH | CARE.
WELL, MAYBE YOU DON'T THINK [M GOOD ENOUGH FOR YOU NOW,
BUT | WILL BE SOMEDAY.
NO, GIL, YOU'RE A GREAT DEAL TOO GOOD FOR ME.
BUT YOU WANT SOMEONE WHO'LL ADORE YOU;
SOMEONE WHO'LL BE HAPPY JUST TO HANG ON YOUR ARM
AND BUILD A HOME FOR YOU
| WOULDN'T.
ANNE, THAT'S NOT WHAT 'M LOOKING FOR AT ALL.
WE'D END UP LIKE TWO OLD CROWS, FIGHTING ALL THE TIME.
| KNOW I'D BE UNHAPPY,
AND I'D WISH WE'D NEVER DONE IT.
EVERYBODY EXPECTS IT.
YOU MUST FEEL THAT.
WELL THEN, IT WOULD BE FOR ALL THE WRONG REASONS, GIL.
YOU JUST THINK THAT YOU LOVE ME.
ANNE...
I'VE LOVED YOU AS LONG AS | CAN REMEMBER.
| NEED YOU.
| CAN'T GO AWAY KNOWING THAT IF I'D JUST...
| PROMISE THAT I'LL ALWAYS BE HERE IF YOU NEED ME.
GOOD FRIENDS ARE ALWAYS TOGETHER IN SPIRIT.
LET'S NOT CHANGE, GIL.
LET'S JUST GO ON BEING GOOD FRIENDS.
[ Heavy sigh ]
FRIENDS, HUH?
| THOUGHT WE WERE KINDRED SPIRITS.
PLEASE SAY YES.
| CAN'T.
GIL, I'M SO DESPERATELY SORRY.
[ Sigh ]
[ Chirping of crickets ]
[ Honking of car horn |] WHOA!
[ Neighing of horse ] WHOA!
LADY, GET OUT OF THE WAY.
WHOA!
WHAT THE HECK ARE YOU DOING, LADY?
HAVE YOU ANY IDEA HOW DIFFICULT IT IS
TO REPLACE ONE OF THESE LANTERNS?
YOU HAD NO BUSINESS TAKING THE RIGHT-OF-WAY.
YOU HAD NO BUSINESS TO BE OUT HERE ALONE
IN THE DARK WITHOUT A LANTERN.
ARE ALL MOTORISTS AS BOLD AS YOU?
| ENJOY BEING OUT ALONE AT NIGHT.
ANY GENTLEMAN WOULD HAVE HAD THE DECENCY TO STOP.
| WAS HOPING WE'D MEET AGAIN.
"VE BEEN WONDERING FOR SEVERAL WEEKS EXACTLY WHO YOU WERE."
'M SORRY | WASN'T ABLE TO INTRODUCE MYSELF
THAT DAY ON THE BEACH.
CAPTAIN... | HAVE NO DESIRE TO BE INTRODUCED,
THANK YOU.
I'LL BET NO ONE'S EVER TOLD
HOW BECOMING RED HAIR CAN BE IN THE MOONLIGHT.
ACTUALLY LOTS OF PEOPLE HAVE.
WHY DON'T YOU TIE THE HORSE UP?
"LL TAKE WHEREVER YOU WANT TO GO."
YOU CAN COME BACK FOR THE BUGGY IN THE MORNING.
I'LL DO NO SUCH THING.
SUIT YOURSELF.
JUST TRYING TO BE A GENTLEMAN.
[| Whinnying of horse |.
DON'T GIVE YOURSELF AIRS.
YOU ARE IN A CLASS ENTIRELY BY YOURSELF.
(singing) OH PROMISE ME THAT SOMEDAY YOU AND I... (singing)
[ Giggling ]
(singing) WILL TAKE OUR LOVE TOGETHER TO SOME SKIES (singing)
(singing) WHEN WE... Both: [ Giggling ]
(singing) ...ALONE AND LOVE RENEW... (singing)
IF THE MINISTER'S WIFE ATTEMPTS TO DOTHIS PIECE, | SHALL FAINT.
| CAN'T ALLOW IT.
(singing) ...FLOWERS BLUE...
| Giggling | CAN'T YOU JUST SEE.
THE BUTTONS POPPING OFF HER CORSET.
OH STOP, ANNE.
OH, 'M GOING TO BE SICK.
NOW, NOW, THIS IS YOU,
NERVOUSLY SWEEPING UP THE AISLE ON YOUR FATHER'S ARM,
YOUR BLACK CURLS FROSTED OVER
WITH THE FILM OF YOUR DELICATE CHIFFON VEIL.
THE PERFECT BRIDE.
YOU LOOK INTO FRED'S RED FACE AND WHISPER,
"W DO." OH, NO.
DON'T BE MEAN.
JUST PROMISE ME ONE THING.
IF HE FAINTS, MAKE SURE YOU CATCH HIM.
[ Scratching of record ]
DIANA?
DIANA BARRY, WHAT IN HEAVEN'S NAME IS GOING ON?
NOW YOU'VE DONE IT.
DIANA, ANSWER ME.
NOTHING, MOTHER.
WE'RE JUST REHEARSING THE WEDDING MARCH.
WELL FOR PITY'S SAKE, DON'T MARCH THROUGH THE CEILING.
OH, I'M SO NERVOUS, ANNE.
| DON'T KNOW HOW I'M GOING TO GET THROUGH THIS TOMORROW.
YOU'LL BE ALL RIGHT.
EVERYONE SURVIVES THE CEREMONY.
IT'S AFTERWARDS... OH, YOU'RE SO SMUG.
JUST WAIT TILL YOUR TURN COMES, MISS ANNE.
NO, | HAVE DEFI-NITELY DECIDED ON A CAREER OVER MARRIAGE.
| THINK I'D LIKE TO BE A NUN.
WOULDN'T IT BE WONDERFUL TO BE THE BRIDE OF HEAVEN?
OH, BUT THEN, I'M NOT CATHOLIC.
AND I'D HARDLY QUALIFY FOR THAT SORT OF CAREER.
WELL, WHAT ABOUT A NURSE?
THAT'S A ROMANTIC PROFESSION,
SMOOTHING FEVERED BROWS,
AND SOME HANDSOME MILLINAIRE PATIENT
FALLING MADLY IN LOVE WITH YOU,
AND CARRYING YOU OFF TO THE MEDITERRANEAN.
| CAN'T GIVE IT UP FOR THE PROSAIC REALITY OF GILBERT.
HE PROPOSED, YOU KNOW...
AND | REFUSED.
YOU WHAT?
YES.
ANNE, ARE YOU OUT OF YOUR MIND?
DON'T SCOLD ME, DIANA.
CAN'T YOU UNDERSTAND?
OH, ANNE, | CAN'T BELIEVE IT.
| THOUGHT ALL THIS GING ON ABOUT YOU IDEALS WAS A COVER-UP
BECAUSE HE HADN'T ASKED YOU YET.
YOU ACTUALLY SAID NO?
AFTER TWO YEARS OF FLIRTING,
THIS IS SCANDALOUS.
YOU TAKE THAT BACK, DIANA BARRY.
"VE NEVER FLIRTED WITH HIM."
GIL AND | HAVE ONLY EVER BEEN GOOD FRIENDS.
| EVEN STEERED CLEAR OF GILBERT BECAUSE OF YOU.
HOW COULD YOU, ANNE?
| KNOW... | DON'T LOVE HIM.
I'M SURE HE DESPISES ME NOW.
AND YOU DESISE ME
AND | DESPISE MYSELF.
(MSO HUMILIATED OVER THIS WHOLE STUPID THING.
YOU POOR DARLING.
"VE NO RIGHT TO SCOLD."
THINGS ARE SO MIXED UP IN REAL LIFE, ANNE.
EY'RE NEVER AS CLEAR AS THEY ARE INROMANTIC NOVELS.
[ Wedding music |
(singing) OH PROMISE ME THAT SOMEDAY YOU AND | (singing)
(singing) WILL TAKE OUR LOVE TOGETHER TO SOME SKIES... (singing)
| Mixed chatter |.
YOUR PARENTS ARE COMING.
OH! OH, ANNE, | SHALL DIE.
I'M SO NERVOUS, I KNOW I'M GOING TO FAINT, AUNT JO.
IF YOU DO, (LL DRAG YOU DOWN TO THE RAINWATER HOG SHED
AND DROP YOU IN. HERE. LET ME SEE YOU.
DON'T YOU FRET.
OH, YOU LOOK LOVELY.
Mr. Barry: WELL, EVERYTHING'S ALL READY.
"VE GIVEN THE MINISTER THE SIGNAL."
OH, MY DARLING, I'M LOSING YOU FOREVER.
OH! OH!
NOW, NOW, DON'T GET ALL SENTIMENTAL, ELIZABETH.
YOU STILL HAVE MINNIE MAY.
TEARS AREN'T LUCKY AT WEDDINGS.
(singing) ..OH PROMISE ME
(singing) HEARING GOD'S MESSAGE WHILE THE ORGAN ROLLS (singing)
(singing) ITS MIGHTY MUSIC TO OUR VERY SOULS (singing)
(singing) ALOVE THAT'S PERFECT AND A LIFE WITH PEACE (singing)
(singing) OH PROMISE ME
(singing) OH PROMISE...
WHAT A FINE-LOOKING PAIR.
YOU WON'T WIN THAT BLYTHE BOY BACK BY PUNISHING HIM.
| WONDER WHY EVERYONE SEEMS TO THINK
| OUGHT TO BE WITH GILBERT BLYTHE.
DIANA...
[ Cheering/applause | [ Mixed greetings |]
EXCUSE ME.
MOODY SPURGEON.
Anne: GOODNESS, YOU LOOK OLDER.
IN YOUR NEW CELLULOID COLLAR.
THANKS, ANNE. YOU LOOK DASHING Y-YOURSELF.
Y-YOU LOOKED AS GOOD AS THE BRIDE.
WELL, HOW SWEET OF YOU, MOODY,
TO ASK JOSIE TO THE WEDDING.
YOU KNOW, | WAS AFRAID YOU MIGHTN'T HAVE BEEN INVITED.
ISN'T SHE PRECIOUS, MOODY?
YOU WORE THAT SWEET OLD DRESS
TO FANNY EMERSON'S WEDDING LAST YEAR THOUGH,
DIDN'T YOU, ANNE?
YOU KNOW WHAT THEY SAY,
"PWICE A BRIDESMAID, NEVER A BRIDE.'
THAT'S "THREE TIMES A BRIDESMAID,"
NOT TWICE, JOSIE.
BUT THEN YOU'RE SO FORTUNATE.
THE ONLY THING YOU'VE EVER HAD TO WEAR TWICE
IS A SOUR EXPRESSION.
NOW, DON'T YOU FORGET TO SAVE ME A WALTZ.
| WON'T, ANNE.
ALL RIGHT. | WAS JUST TRYING TO BE POLITE.
YOUR TURN, GILBERT...
AH, EXCUSE ME A MOMENT, WON'T YOU, CHRISTINE?
MOODY, JOSIE. GILBERT.
WHAT'S WRONG? | DON'T KNOW.
ANNE, WAIT.
PLEASE, GIL.
WHERE ARE YOU GOING?
I'M LEAVING.
MARILLA TOOK RACHEL BACK EARLY.
SHE WAS ILL, AND...
| DON'T FEEL VERY WELL EITHER.
I'LL DRIVE YOU BACK.
WHAT ABOUT YOUR FRIEND?
| CAN EXPLAIN. SHE WON'T MIND.
SHE LOOKS LIKE A LOVELY
AND ACCOMPLISHED YOUNG LADY, GIL.
IT'S NOT CHRISTINE | CARE ABOUT.
THERE'S SOMEONE ELSE, ISN'T THERE?
NO, GIL, HONESTLY THERE ISN'T.
| DON'T CARE FOR ANYONE IN THAT WAY,
AND I LIKE YOU MORE THAN ANYBODY.
ANNE, I'LL WAIT.
EVEN IF | THOUGHT YOU CARED JUST A LITTLE.
| DO CARE, GIL.
| ALWAYS HAVE.
BUT | CAN NEVER, NEVER LOVE YOU IN THE WAY THAT YOU WANT ME TO.
I'M HAPPY AS 1 AM.
| WON'T EVER MARRY.
YOU'LL MARRY ALL RIGHT.
SOME FOOL WHO'LL SIT AND READ TENNYSON BY FIRE LIGHT, NO DOUBT...
AND BUILD YOU YOUR CASTLES IN THE SKY.
|IKNOW YOU.
PLEASE, GIL, | DON'T MEAN TO HURT YOU,
BUT YOU'LL SEE THAT 'M RIGHT BY AND BY,
WHEN YOU FALL FOR SOMEONE ELSE.
YOU HAVEN'T HURT ME REALLY.
IT'S JUST THAT I'VE...
FOOLED MYSELF INTO THINKING THAT YOU LOVED ME, THAT'S ALL.
GIL, PLEASE.
| HOPE HE BREAKS YOUR HEART...
WHOEVER HE IS.
YOU DON'T UNDERSTAND.
THEN MAYBE YOU'LL COME TO YOUR SENSES.
ANNE!
OH, YOU LOOK POSITIVELY RADIANT.
YOU LOOK LIKE YOU'VE SEEN A GHOST.
GILBERT SPOKE TO ME AGAIN.
DIANA, | FEEL LIKE I'VE CUT OFF HIS RIGHT ARM.
WOULD YOU PLEASE GO AND TALK TO HIM?
| KNOW HE'LL LISTEN TO YOU.
HURRY UP, DIANA.
| DON'T... | DON'T KNOW WHEN OR... OR HOW, BUT...
"LL TRY."
GOODBYE, ANNE.
FAREWELL, MY BELOVED.
(music)
[ Cheering ]
Christine: YOU'RE WRONG, TILLIE.
| THOUGHT ANNE SHIRLEY LOOKED LOVELY BESIDE DIANA.
CHRISTINE STEWART, YOU'RE TOO KIND.
| CAN'T BELIEVE YOU DIDN'T NOTICE ANNE STARING AT GILBRT,
JUST TO MAKE HIM JEALOUS.
|KNOW THAT GILIS VERY FOND OF ANNE,
BUT HE CERTAINLY ISN'T JEALOUS. HUH!
SHE'S JUST TRYING DESPERATELY TO WIN HIM BACK FROM YOU.
Christine: | DON'T THINK IT'S THAT AT ALL.
BESIDES, GIL AND | ARE ONLY FRIENDS.
WELL, | THINK ANNE SHIRLEY HAS FAR TOO BIG
AN OPINION OF HERSELF.
(music)
WHY, ANNE,
| THOUGHT YOU WERE GOING TO STAY AT THE BARRYS' FOR THE BONFIRE.
WHY DID YOU COME HOME SO EARLY?
DIANA... SHE WAS THE BRIDE OF MY DREAMS.
BUT SHE AND FRED HAVE LEFT NOW AND...
| FEEL TIRED AND... ANXIOUS.
| DON'T KNOW.
PERHAPS | SHOULD ACCEPT MISS STACEY'S OFFER IN KINGSPORT.
I'D LIKE TO SEE AND HEAR NEW PLACES.
| COULD GET A WHOLE BUNCH OF IDEAS | COULD WRITE STORIES FROM.
RACHEL WAS FEELING PRETTY DISCOURAGED TODAY AT THE WEDDING,
HAVING TO MOVE WEST AND LIVE WITH HER BY AND ALL.
AND THE THOUGHT CAME TO ME THAT PERHAPS | SHOULD ASK HER
TO BOARD WITH ME INSTEAD OF THE PICARD GIRL.
| HAVEN'T SAID ANYTHING TO HER.
IWANTED YOUR OPINION.
WELL, IT WOULD BE YOUR DECISION, MARILLA.
BUT ARE YOU SURE?
WELL, SHE HAS HER FAULTS, | KNOW.
BUT SHE HAS BEEN MY NEAREST NEIGHBOUR
FOR 45 YEARS, AND...
I'D RATHER PUT UP WITH HER THAN LOSE HER.
PLEASE DON'T DO THIS BECAUSE YOU FEEL BADLY ON MY ACCOUNT.
OH, STUFF AND NONSENSE.
| CAN BE CIVIL WITH RACHEL,
AS LONG AS SHE STAYS OUT OF MY KITCHEN.
WE'LL BE QUITE CAPABLE OF LOOKING AFTER THE FARM WITH MR. BARRY'S HELP.
MARILLA...
DO YOU NEVER WISH YOU'D ADOPTED A BOY
LIKE YOU INTENDED TO?
| MEAN, HE COULD HAVE RUN THIS FARM,
AND SAVED YOU ALL THIS TROUBLE.
ANNE SHIRLEY, | WOULDN'T TRADE YOU FOR A DOZEN BOYS.
NOW YOU JUST MIND THAT.
WAS IT A BOY THAT GOT THE BACHELOR OF ARTS,
AND WON THE ROLLINGS RELIABLE STORY CONTEST,
NOW WAS IT?
LL MISS YOU. "LL MISS MY GIRL."
PROMISE ME YOU WON'T STAY AWAY FOREVER.
(music)
| NEVER THOUGHT OF LIVING AS FAR OFF THE ROAD AS GREEN GABLES,
BUT I... (D RATHER LIVE AT THE BOTTOM OF A WELL
THAN LEAVE AVONLEA.
WELL, | KNOW HOW GRATEFUL ANNE IS TO YOU FOR STAYING.
WELL, SHE WAS ALWAYS ONE TO LEAP INTO THINGS
WHEN SHE'D MADE HER MIND UP TOIT.
IT'S A BLESSING SHE'S OFF TO A LADIES' ACADEMY, THAT'S WHAT.
| DON'T APPROVE OF THEM CO-EDUCATIONAL INSTITUTIONS,
AND | NEVER HAVE. ALL THE GIRLS
FLIRTING WITH ALL THE BOYS.
THEY DO STUDY A LITTLE, RACHEL.
HUMPH. PRECIOUS LITTLE.
HOWEVER HER PUPILS WILL BE WELL ENOUGH BEHAVED,
IF THIS SCHOOLS AS WELL-TO-DO AS SHE CLAIMS.
| CAN'T IMAGINE I'VE FORGOTTEN A THING.
Anne: YOU'VE ALL BEEN SO HELPFUL.
MIND HOW YOU WERE RAISED NOW,
AND GO TO CHURCH REGULARLY, ANNE,
AND BE CAREFUL WHAT FRIENDS YOU MAKE.
Marilla: BE SURE TO PUT ON YOUR WARM UNDER-CLOTHES.
WHEN THE WEATHER GETS CHILLY.
Rachel: YES, AND BE CAREFUL OF YOUR HEALTH WHATEVER YOU DO.
AND YOU LET US HEAR FROM YOU WHEN YOU'VE SETTLED.
Rachel: GOODBYE, ANNE. GOODBYE.
MAKE SURE EVERYTHING'S WELL TAGGED
WHEN YOU PUT IT ON THE TRAIN.
DON'T WORRY, WE'LL TAKE GOOD CARE OF HER AT THE STATION.
HURRY UP NOW. YOU'LL BE LATE.
GOOD LUCK.
GOODBYE, MARILLA.
| DON'T KNOW WHAT I'D DO WITHOUT YOU.
YOU'VE BOTH BEEN SO WONDERFUL.
BUT | WON'T BE GONE FOR LONG,
AND | PROMISE "LL WRITE AS OFTEN ASI CAN."
GOODBYE.
(music)
WELL, MARILLA,
| NEVER WOULD HAVE BELIEVED AN ORPHACOULD TURN OUT SO FINE.
NO ONE COULD DENY SHE'S REAL TALL AND STYLISH NOW.
NOBODY AT ALL.
Marilla: | CAN'T HELP REMEMBERING HER.
AS ALITTLE GIRL.
AWFUL HARD | WAS BEWILDERED,
TRYING TO MANAGE HER.
MATTHEW UNDERSTOOD HER BETTER.
WELL, IT'S TO YOUR CREDIT YOU'VE CHANGED HER AS MUCH AS YOU DID.
OH, SHE HASN'T CHANGED THAT MUCH.
NOT REALLY.
IT'S US THAT'S CHANGED, RACHEL.
(music)
HOW I'VE LONGED FOR THIS MOMENT, DIANA,
AND NOW THAT IT'S STARING ME IN THE FACE,
| CAN'T BEAR THE THOUGHT OF LEAVING.
WE SAW GIL BLYTHE OFF TO MEDICAL SCHOOL LAST WEEK.
DID HE... SAY ANYTHING, DIANA?
| THINK HE UNDERSTANDS, ANNE.
(music)
[ Chugging of train |.
ANNE? ANNE SHIRLEY!
OH, THERE YOU ARE.
OH, MISS STACEY.
IT FEELS LIKE DECADES.
OH, UP ALL NIGHT ON THAT DREADFUL TRAIN,
YOU MUST BE EXHAUSTED.
OH, | FEEL BROKEN-DOWN AND GREEN AND PROVINCIAL,
AND ONLY
FOR PITY'S SAKE PLEASE TAKE ME SOMEPLACE
WHERE | CAN HEAR MYSELF THINK.
"VE GOT A CAB WAITING JUST OUTSIDE."
WHERE ARE YOUR LUGGA TICKETS?
THE DRIVER CAN TAKE CARE OF YOUR TRUNK.
IF YOU WEREN'T HERE, MISS STACEY,
| THINK | SHOULD JUST SIT DOWN AND BURST INTO TEARS.
WELL, | CAN'T TELL YOU
JUST HOW HAPPY | AM TO HAVE YOU HERE, ANNE.
AFTER ALL, WHY BE A MEMBER OF THE BOARD OF GOVERNORS OF AN INSTITUTION,
IF YOU CAN'T PULL A FEW STRINGS?
OH, MISS STACEY, YOU DIDN'T!
YES, | DID.
(music)
Anne: | INTEND TO KEEP UP WITH MY WRITING.
THIS QUAINT OLD TOWN WILL BE A WONDERFUL INSPIRATION.
WELL, | THINK YOUR YOUTH AND VITALITY
WILL MAKE AN ENORMOUS CONTRIBUTION TO OUR LADIES' COLLEGE.
AFTER ALL, YOU WERE MY PRIZE PUPIL IN AVONLEA.
Anne: I'M SO NERVOUS ILWON'T MEET WITH THEIR EXPECTATIONS.
Miss Stacey: OH, NONSENSE.
THEY MAY BE PRIVILEGED YOUNG LADIES FROM WEALTHY FAMILIES,
BUT THEY'RE SPOILED AND PAMPERED, MANY OF THEM.
(music)
GREAT JEHOSOPHAT! WHAT RICHNESS!
THIS IS FAR MORE GRACIOUS
THAN | EVER DREAMED COULD EXIST.
[ Rapping on door |.
GOOD MORNING, MAAM. GOOD MORNING.
COULD YOU PLEASE TELL MISS PRINGLE THAT MISS STACEY
AND MISS ANNE SHIRLEY ARE HERE TO SEE HER.
| THINK YOU'LL BE QUITE COMFORTABLE HERE.
MRS. TOM PRINGLE ISON THE ALUMNI.
SHE'S BEEN BOARDING TEACHERS FROM KINGSPORT LADIES' COLLEGE
FOR 30 YEARS NOW.
MISS STACEY, HOW DELIGHTFUL TO SEE YOU.
AND YOU, MRS. PRINGLE.
MAY | INTRODUCE YOU TO MISS ANNE SHIRLEY
OF AVONLEA, PRINCE EDWARD ISLAND?
HOW DO YOU DO?
SHE'S OUR NEW ENGLISH TEACHER
AT KINGSPORT LADIES' COLLEGE,
WHO YOU'LL BE BOARDING THIS YEAR.
SHOULD | HAVE THE CABBY BRING HER TRUNK?
OBVIOUSLY YOU DID NOT RECEIVE MY LETTER.
I'M AFRAID I'VE DECIDED NOT TO TAKE HER, MISS STACEY.
I'M REALLY RATHER TIRED OF BEING BOTHERED
BOARDING STAFF.
MY GIRLS ARE FINISHED, AS YOU KNOW,
AND | REALLY SPEND SO LITTLE TIME
WITH THE ALUMNI.
BUT MRS. PRINGLE...
| DO APOLOGIZE FOR THE INCONVENIENCE.
GOOD DAY, MISS STACEY.
NOT AT ALL.
GOOD DAY.
HOW TYPICALLY PRINGLE.
AS SMOOTH AS CREAM, EVEN WHEN THEY'RE WORKING AGAINST YOU.
WELL, WE SHALL SEE ABOUT THAT. HMM?
WHAT IS IT, MISS STACEY?
KINGSPORT IS FULL OF PRINGLES AND HALF-PRINGLES.
THEY'RE THE OLD MONEY THAT RULES THIS TOWN,
AND MRS. TOM PRING BOSSES THE WHOLE TRIBE.
| WAS AFRAID THEY'D BE DOWN ON YOU.
WHY SHOULD THEY BE? I'M A TOTAL STRANGER.
ONE OF THEIR COUSINS, MISS AMY PRINGLE BOOTHE,
APPLIED FOR YOUR POSITION,
AND WAS ABYSMALLY LESS QUALIFIED, | MIGHT ADD.
HOWEVER, WHEN THE BOARD ANNOUNCED
THAT THEY HAD ACCEPTED YOUR APPLICATION,
WELL THE WHOLE KIT AND KABOODLE OF THEM
JUST THREW BACK THEIR HEADS AND HOWLED.
UH, KINGSPORT LADIES' COLLEGE, PLEASE, DRIVER.
WELL, THEY'RE NOT GOING TO GET AWAY WITH IT.
THEY CAN'T BOYCOTT THE BOARD'S DECISION.
IT'S UNDEMOCRATIC.
Anne: I'M NOT SURE | QUITE ALWAYS TRUST DEMOCRACY.
THEY'VE ALWAYS RULED THE ROOST HERE, THE WHOLE CLAN OF THEM.
POLITICALLY AND SOCIALLY.
WELL, THEY MAY OWN THE LUMBER MILL,
THE RAILWAY, THE GAS WORKS AND THE WOOLEN MILL,
BUT | WILL NOT ALLOW THE PRINGLES TO DICTATE OUR SYSTEM OF EDUCATION.
YOU CANT IMAGINE HOW NERVOUS | AM NOW.
[ Chuckling ]
(music)
MISS KATHANE BROOKE IS THE PRINCIPAL HERE.
A BIT OFA MARTINET IN MATTERS OF DISCIPLINE,
FROM TIME TO TIME, BUT I'M SURE
THAT WE CAN RESOLVE WHATEVER LITTLE DIFFERENCES OF OPINION
THAT MIGHT ARISE.
(music)
[ Rapping on door |.
COME IN.
GOOD MORNING, MISS BROOKE.
MISS STACEY. PLEASE FORGIVE THE INTRUSION,
BUT | WAS JUST SO EAGER TO INTRODUCE YOU
TO OUR NEW ENGLISH PROFESSOR, MISS ANNE SHIRLEY.
ONE OF THE BRIGHTEST STARS OF MY ENTIRE TEACHING CAREER.
SHE HAS RECENTLY PUBLISHED A SHORT WORK OF FICTION AS WELL.
WELCOME TO KINGSPORT, MISS SHIRLEY.
PLEASE SIT DOWN.
THANK YOU. I'M VERY PLEASED TO BE HERE.
MISS STACEY HAS RECOMMENDED YOU SO HIGHLY TO US.
| HADN'T EXPECTED ONE SO ACCOMPLISHED
TO BE SO YOUNG...
A FAULT WHICH TIME WILL CURE ALL TOO SOON.
MISS BROOKE, THERE SEEMS TO BE SOME SORT OF MIX-UP
REGARDING MISS SHIRLEY'S ACCOMMODATIONS,
BUT | WAS SURE THAT YOU WOULDN'T OBJECT
HAVING HER STAY HERE AT THE SCHOOL
WITH YOUR OUT-OF-TOWN BOARDING STUDENTS.
I'M SURE YOU'LL FIND HER TO BE THE PERFECT DEN-MOTHER FOR THEM.
WE HAVE NO NEED OF MATERNAL AFFECTATIONS
IN THIS INSTITUTE, MISS STACEY.
WE GOVERN BY RULES AND REGULATIONS.
WHICH DO REQUIRE A LEAVEN IN THE LUMP
FROM TIME TO TIME, MS BROOKE.
SHALL WE HAVE THE GROUNDSMAN BRING IN MISS SHIRLEY"S THINGS?
"LL HAVE THE MAID PREPARE HER ROOM."
THANK YOU SO MUCH.
SHE IS AN ABSOLUTE SERGEANT-MAJOR, MISS STACEY.
HOW SHALL I EVER TOLERATE HER SARCASM?
NONETHELESS SHE IS A DEDICATED TEACHER,
IF SOMEWHAT OF AN EXCES-SIVE DISCIPLINARIAN.
YOU JUST KEEP YOUR CHIN UP,
AND YOU GIVE IT YOUR VERY BEST,
IF ONLY TO SPITE THEM ALL.
YOU KNOW HOW HIGHLY | REGARD YOUR ABILITIES, ANNE.
| SHALL DO VERY BEST TO RISE TO THE OCCASION.
GOOD GIRL.
NOW YOU WANT TO GET YOURSELF ORGANIZED
BEFORE THE START OF CLASSES TOMORROW.
OH, HO-HO!
OH. THANK YOU FOR EVERYTHING, MISS STACEY.
WE CAN DO THE REST OF OUR CATCHING UP LATER.
(music)
IN FUTURE, MISS SHIRLEY, YOU WILL KINDLY REMEMBER
THAT YOU ARE NOT AT LIBERTY TO MAKE ANY CHANGES,
NO MATTER HOW MINOR, TO THE CONVENTIONS OF THIS INSTITUTION.
/M SORRY, I...
| WAS JUST SO MOVED BY YOUR INSPIRING QUOTATION,
|IWANTED TO EMBELLISH IT.
DON'T PATRONIZE ME.
WHAT IS TO BE THE PILL IN AL THIS JAM, MISS SHIRLEY?
WHY NOTHING. I...
| JUST THOUGHT IT WAS A TREMENDOUSLY UPLIFTING IDEA,
THAT'S ALL.
'M GLAD YOU SPELL YOUR NAME WITH A °K'.
KATHARINE WITH A °K" IS SO MUCH MORE ALLURING
THAN CATHERINE WITH A °C".
A "C' ALWAYS LOOKS SO SMUG.
WE HAVE 50 YOUNG LADIES IN OQUR CHARGE,
FROM THE MOST PRIVILEGED FAMILIES IN THE MARITIMES.
MY METHODS ADMONISH ANYTHING BEYOND THE STANDARDS
OF THE UTMOST DECORUM.
THIS IS NOT A PUBLIC SCHOOL OF THE KIND
THAT YOU ARE USED TO, MISS SHIRLEY.
OUR STUDENTS DO NOT REQUIRE EMBELLISHMENT.
SIMPLE STRAIGHT-FORWARD ADHERENCE TO RULES AND REGULATIONS
WHICH | HAVE CLEARLY DELINEATED FOR YOU,
MISS SHIRLEY.
OUR STUDENTS ARE DRILLED IN THEIR STUDIES
AT THE BEGINNING OF EACH CLASS.
BEDTIME AND MEALTIME WILL BE STRICTLY OBSERVED BY OUR 15 BOARDERS.
YOU, MISS SHIRLEY, WILL SEE TOIT
THAT THE BOARDERS ESPECIALLY
ADHERE TO THE UTMOST ORDERLINESS.
| AM PLACING THEM UNDER YOUR CONTINUAL DIRECTION.
1AM REFERRED TO
BY THE ENTIRE FACULTY AS BROOKE.
YOU MAY DO THE SAME.
YES, MISS BROOKE.
| UNDERSTAND YOU HAVE EXTRAORDINARY TALENTS.
| LOOK FORWARD TO OBSERVING THEM.
| AM GLAD | MEET WITH YOUR APPROVAL IN SOME APPROXIMATION.
WE SHALL SEE.
YOU ARE HERE ASA RESULT OF THE BOARD'S DECISION, NOT MINE.
[ Jangling of electric bell ]
FOR A COUNTRY-SCHOOL MA'RM, YOU'LL FIND
THAT WE ARE EQUIPPED WITH THE MOST MODERN EFFICIENCIES,
DUE TO THE TREMENDOUS FINANCIAL SUPPORT
OF CERTAIN PROMINENT FAMILIES.
Girls: [ Singing |]
IN FACT, WE ARE THE FIRST SCHOOL IN THE PROVINCE
TO HAVE A TELEPHONE.
(singing) ALL THINGS BRIGHT AND BEAUTIFUL (singing)
(singing) ALL CREATURES GREAT AND SMALL (singing)
(singing) ALL THINGS WISE AND WONDERFUL (singing)
(singing) THE LORD GOD MADE THEM ALL (singing)
WELCOME TO A NEW YEAR.
| TRUST YOU GIRLS ARE READY TO DRIVE INTO THE FIRST SESSION WITH DETERMINATION.
YOU ALL KNOW MISS McKAY, MATHEMATICS AND SCIENCE,
MISS KERR, HISTORY AND GEOGRAPHY,
AND MISS SHIRLEY WILL BE YOUR NEW TEACHER,
RESPONSIBLE FOR ENGLISH AND LITERATURE,
AS WELL AS ALL STUDENT BOARDERS.
MISS SHIRLEY WILL BE LIVING IN THE SCHOOL WITH US,
AND WILL HAVE DIRECT SUPERVISORY AUTHORITY.
LET US GET TO WORK THEN,
WITH NO NONSENSE.
PLEASE ORGANIZE YOURSELVES INTO FORMS.
[ Blasting of whistle ]
FORM ONE, DO YOU CALL THAT A STRAIGHT LINE?
EMMELINE HARRIS...
STEP FORWARD.
IF YOU INTEND TO MAKE A HABIT OF THIS,
| WILL HAVE NO CHOICE BUT TO DETAIN YOU AFTER CLASS.
STEP BACK.
LEARN TO RESPOND TO SIGNALS ON THE ELECTRIC BELL AS WELL.
'D MUCH PREFER TO INVENT TITLES FOR EACH GROUP,
LIKE A SORORITY.
WHAT ABOUT...
TUDOR, KENT AND WINDSOR?
1AM NOT INTERESTED IN FAIRY TALES.
YOU MUST LEARN TO USE THE MODERN CONVENIENCES
OF OUR SYSTEM.
AT RECESS, | WILL EMPLOY THE ELECTRIC BELL.
[ Blasting of whistles |.
YOUR ROOM IS DOWN THE HALL, FIRST DOOR.
[ Blasting of whistle ]
PERHAPS YOU THINK YOU ARE ABOVE RULES, MISS SHIRLEY?
Girls: [ Giggling |.
Anne: [ Clearing of throat ]
WELL... OFF YOU GO, GIRLS.
[ Giggling/chattering |.
Anne: PLEASE, GIRLS.
QUIET PLEASE.
GOOD MORNING.
[ Clearing of throat ]
| WOULD LIKE TO BEGIN BY SHARING WITH YOU
WHAT A GREAT PRIVILEGE IT WOULD BE FOR ME
TO SHARE WITH YOU... UH!
Girls: [ Laughing nastily |.
OH, BLAST! [ Groan of pain |
1O SHARE WITH YOU MY GREAT LOVE OF ENGLISH LITERATURE
DURING THE FORTHCOMING YEAR.
LET'S HOPE I'M ALITTLE LIGHTER ON SHAKESPEARE
THAN | AM ON MY FEET.
[ Clearing of throat ]
[ Snapping of chalk |]
NEVER MIND.
| HAD A SPEECH PREPARED,
BUT IT DOESN'T SEEM VERY IMPORTANT RIGHT NOW.
MY NAME IS ANNE SHIRLEY,
AND | KNOW WE SHALL ALL BECOME GOOD FRIENDS IN NO TIME.
Girls: [ Chanting ] 7 TIMES 21S 14.7 TIMES 31S 21.
7 TIMES 4 IS 28.7 TIMES SIS...
| COME ROM A LITTLE TOWN CALLED AVONLEA ON PRINCE EDWARD ISLAND,
WHERE | HAVE BEEN TEACHING FOR THE PAST TWO YEARS.
SO THIS IS MY FIRST TIME IN A PRIVATE SCHOOL POSITION.
AND | HOPE THAT YOU WILL ALL BE ABLE TO GIVE ME LOTS OF ASSISTANCE.
NOW... WHEN | CALL OUT YOUR NAME,
ANSWER "HERE".
PRINGLE, MYRA C.
PRINGLE, REBECCA A.
AREN'T THESE YOUR NAMES?
NO, MISS, PERHAPS THE CLASS LISTS HAVE BEEN MIXED UP.
Girls: [ Giggling |.
OH, ALL RIGHT,
GIVE ME YOUR NAMES THEN, ONE AT A TIME,
STARTING HERE, THE YOUNG LADY IN THE FRONT ROW.
LAST NAME FIRST, AND AGE.
OPPENER, FANNY I. OPPENER.
THERE ARE TWO "Ps" IN OPPENER.
14.
GIRDLE, MYRTLE N. GIRDLE.
HEIND. THAT'S H-E-I-N-D.
ALICE B. HEIND. 14.
BALL. WILMA I. BALL.
33.
ACTUALLY I'M FROM THE ROLLINGS RELIABLE BAKING COMPANY,
AND WE WERE WONDERING WHEN YOU'D BE AVAILABLE
TO REWRITE OUR LABELS.
THAT'S ENOUGH!
| HADN'T ANTICIPATED A CLASS
WHOSE PARENTS WERE SUCH NITWITS AT NAMING THEIR CHILDREN.
HARRIS. EMMELINE HARRIS. 13.
AND DON'T BELIEVE ANY OF THEM, MISS SHIRLEY.
WHAT DO YOU MEAN?
THEY'RE JUST PULLING YOUR LEG BECAUSE THEY'RE PRINGLES,
AND THEY THINK THEY CAN GET AWAY WITH IT.
OLD TELESCOPE-EYES HERE WOULDN'T KNOW A PRINGLE
IF SHE WERE FACE-TO-FACE WITH ONE.
Girls: [ Laughing nastily |.
SINCE MISSES FANNY EYEOPPENER, MYRTLE ENGIRDLE,
ALICE BEHEIND AND WILMA EYEBALL FIND THEM-SELVES SO TERRIBLY WITTY,
THEY WILL WRITE OUT AN ACCURATE CLASS LIST 100 TIMES,
TODAY AFTER CLASSES, FOR MY BENEFIT.
NOW, OPEN YOUR READERS, PLEASE.
[| Screaming |.
Girls: [| Screaming |
[ Quavering |] PLEASE...
M-M-MISS SHIRLEY...
| Screaming continues |.
Girl: OH, MISS SHIRLEY, HELP HER.
[ Murmurs of concern |.
Anne: EMMELINE HARRIS,
TAKE THIS GIRL TO THE LADIES' ROOM.
SOAK THE HANDKERCHEIF IN COLD WATER
AND SEE IF YOU CAN STOP THE BLEEDING.
Girls: [ Chatter/laughter |]
[ Blasting of whistle ]
ALL RIGHT. ALL OF YOU SIT DOWN NOW!
AND REMAIN SEATED.
WHO PUT THE SNAKE IN MY DESK?
WHAT IS YOUR REAL NAME?
JEN PRINGLE, MISS SHIRY.
WAS IT YOU, JEN PRINGLE?
YES, IT WAS.
YOU WILL BE DETAINED AFTER CLASSES TODAY...
AND EVERY DAY FOR THE ENTIRE WEEK.
[ Murmurs of reaction |]
NOW, PLEASE, OPEN UR THIRD FORM READERS, CLASS.
| CAN'T, MISS SHIRLEY.
MY MOTHER EXPECTS ME FOR THE NEXT THREE DAYS
AT THE LADIES' AID SOCIETY RUMMAGE SALE.
WELL, I'M SORRY BUT YOUR MOTHER WILL HAVE TO MAKE OTHER ARRANGEMENTS.
BUT SHE'S PROMISED MY HELP ON THE ORGAN-IZATION COMMITTEE.
| DON'T CARE.
YOU'LL STAY IF | SAY SO.
| SIMPLY CANNOT STAY.
/M SORRY.
WELL THEN, IT'S UP TO YOU, ISN'T IT, JEN PRINGLE?
EITHER YOU STAY AFTER SCHOOL FOR THE WEEK...
OR I'LL HAVE TO MINISTER THE STRAP.
Myra: YOU JUST CAN'T DO THAT, MISS SHIRLEY.
[ Mixed whispers |]
"LL TAKE THE STRAP."
REALLY?
[ Clearing of throat ]
COME HERE THEN, MISS PRINGLE.
PUT OUT YOUR HAND.
[ Impact of Strap on hand |
(music)
OPEN YOUR READERS, CLASS,
AND PLEASE LOOK AT THE FIRST CHAPTER FOR THE REST OF THE PERIOD.
(music)
[ Jangling of electric bell ]
Girls: [ Chattering |.
ARE YOU ALL RIGHT, ESSIE?
I'M AFRAID I'M NOT VERY GOOD AROUND REPTILES.
NEITHER AM I.
YOU'LL GET USED TO ESSIE, MISS SHIRLEY.
SHE FAINTS AT LEAST ONCE A WEEK.
THE DOCTORS SAY HER BLOOD IS WEAK.
THANK YOU, EMMELINE.
DON'T CONCERN YOURSELF ABOUT THE PRINGLE GIRLS EITHER.
THE ONLY PEOPLE THEY LIKE ARE THEMSELVES.
| CAN SAY THAT WITHOUT MALICE,
BECAUSE MY MOTHER WAS A PRINGLE.
BESIDES, | LIKE YOU,
AND | THINK YOU HANDLED THE CLASS VERY INTELLIGENTLY.
(music)
[ Twittering of birds |
[ Mixed chattering |.
YOU TRAITOR, HARRIS.
| GUESS THERE ARE ONLY TWO KINDS OF PEOPLE IN KINGSPORT;
THOSE WHO ARE PRINGLES AND THOSE WHO AREN'T.
SHUT UP, JEN.
| DON'T CARE A SNIT WHAT YOU SAY.
"M HALF-PRINGLE."
HUH, YOUR MOTHER DIDN'T LIVE LONG ENOUGH TO MAKE YOU ANYTHING.
AND MY PAPA SAYS YOUR PAPA
IS THE GREATEST PHILANDERER IN THIS COUNTRY,
SO THAT PRACTICALLY MAKES YOU AN ORPHAN.
Emmeline/Essie: [ Yelps of distress |.
DON'T YOU DARE EVER SAY ANOTHER WORD ABOUT MY FATHER AGAIN.
YOU STUPID, GOOD-FOR-NOTHING GOOSE-EGG.
[ Mixed shouting ]
HE'S A BRUTE, AND MY PAPA SAYS SO.
LET'S SEE HOW BIG YOUR MOUTH IS NOW, JEN PRINGLE.
[ Squealing |
[ Mixed shouting ]
OH, MY GLASSES!
STOP IT!
[ Blasting of whistle ]
THAT IS ENOUGH!
ON YOUR... GET UP THERE.
STAND UP.
HAVE YOU GIRLS NO PROPRIETY?
THIS IS NOT TURKISH BAZAAR.
THEY TRIED TO RUN ME DOWN ON THAT BICYCLE.
YOU LITTLE LIAR!
SHE THREW HER CROQUET MALLET IN THE WHEEL
AND TRIPPED US.
DIDN'T SHE, ESSIE?
| DID NOT, YOU BEAST!
SHE ATTACKED ME.
STOP IT!
| HAVE A GOOD MIND TO EXPEL YOU BOTH FOR SUCH HOOLIGANISM.
BICYCLES ARE FORBIDDEN ON SCHOOL PROPERTY.
THIS CONTRAPTION IS CONFISCATED AS OF THIS MOMENT.
BUT, MISS BROOKE, THE BICYCLE ISN'T MINE.
IT'S MY BROTHER'S.
HE OUGHT NOT TO HAVE BEEN SO FOOLISH
AS TO HAVE ENTRUSTED IT TO YOU.
IT HARDLY SEEMS FAIR TO BE PUNISHING HER BROTHER.
YES, MISS BROOKE, | THINK...
DO YOU NOUNDER-STAND ENGLISH?
Miss Brooke: NOW | WANT YOU TWO GIRLS TO APOLOGIZE TO EACH OTHER,
AND BEHAVE LIKE PROPER YOUNG LADIES.
| AM QUITE PREPARED TO FORGIVE YOUR LACK OF MANNERS.
AND | YOUR RUDE COMMENTS.
THAT'S ENOUGH.
WELL, DON'T STAND THERE LIKE PIGEONS, GIRLS.
GO ALONG.
IF YOU ALLOW AN OQUTBURST LIKE THAT TO OCCUR AGAIN, MISS SHIRLEY,
YOU SHALL HAVE THE BOARD TO RECKON WITH.
LOCK THIS IN THE SHED, McTAVISH.
GO ALONG, GIRLS, DON'T GAWK.
(music)
LOOKING FOR THESE?
JEN!
I'M SORRY ABOUT YOUR SPECTACLES.
WE'LL GET THEM REPLACED.
IT'S NOT THAT.
IT'S WHAT SHE SAID ABOUT MY PAPA.
JUST YOU FORGET ABOUT WHATEVER THEY SAID.
THERE'S NOT AN OUNCE OF TRUTH IN IT.
WE WON'T LET IT SPOIL THE AFTERNOON.
WE DIDN'T GET YOU INTO TROUBLE,
DID WE, MISS SHIRLEY?
DON'T WORRY ABOUT ME.
BROOKE'S JUST AN OLD BATTLE-AXE ANYWAY.
DON'T TELL ANYBODY | SAID THAT.
| ALMOST FAINTED WHEN | SAW HER COME ACROSS THE LAWN.
WELL, SHE'LL COOL OFF IN A FEW DAYS AND...
THEN PLL GET YOUR BROTHER'S BICYCLE BACK.
COME ALONG, AND DON'T YOU GIVE IT ANOTHER WORRY.
Essie: YOU SHOULD HAVE SEEN HER.
WITH HER MOUTH FULL OF MUD, MISS SHIRLEY.
THAT'S THE BEST JEN PRINGLE'S LOOKED IN A LONG TIME.
[ Knocking on door |.
ALL RIGHT, I'M TURNING MY LIGHT OUT NOW, MISS BROOKE.
[ Knking on door |.
Emmeline: MISS SHIRLEY?
EMMELINE! OH, MISS SHIRLEY, YOU'VE GOT TO HELP US.
ESSIE'S BROTHER NEEDS THE BICYCLE INTHE MORNING
FOR HIS DELIVERY JOB, OR HE'LL BE FIRED,
AND HE'S READY TO MURDER ESS.
WE CAN'T GET THE SHED DOORS OPEN.
OH, SHE'S AWFUL SCARED,
AND I'M AFRAID SHE'LL FAINT.
HEAVEN PRESERVE US FROM MISS BROOKE IF SHE DOES.
MR. McTAVISH, THE GROUNDSMAN, KEEPS HIS TOOLS IN HERE.
MAYBE WE COULD SAW THE CHAIN ORICK THE LOCK.
STOP WHIMPERING, ESSIE.
EMMELINE, DO YOU THINK YOU COULD SQUEEZE THROUGH THAT SKYLIGHT UP ABOVE?
UH-HUH, IF | HAD A LADDER.
COME ALONG. I'VE GOT A BETTER IDEA.
(music)
ALL RIGHT, YOU GO DOWN FIRST, AND I'LL SHIMMY DOWN AFTER YOU.
I'M FRIGHTENED. I'M GOING TO FAINT.
OH, JUST HANG ON ANOTHER MOMENT, ESSIE, AND YOU CAN.
IF ANYONE CATCHES US, YOU DON'T PPOSE THEY'LL THINK
WE'RE TRYING TO STEAL ANY-THING, DO YOU, MISS SHIRLEY?
OUR MOTIVES ARE HARDLY IDLE CURIOSITY.
Emmeline: ALL RIGHT.
UNTIE THE END, ESSIE, AND THROW IT DOWN.
[ Whimpering ]
Essie: | DON'T THINK YOU SHOULD DO THIS.
OH, | HOPE THE SKYLIGHT'S NOT LOCKED, MISS SHIRLEY.
WE'RE IN LUCK. MR. McTAVISH HAS AN ARMY OF TOOLS DOWN HERE.
GOOD, NOW IF WE CAN JUST... [ Yelping ]
OH, MISS SHIRLEY!
[ Shrieking ]
BED SHEETS!
WELL NOW, ANNE SHIRLEY, WHERE'S THE FIRE?
[ Groan of despair |
[ Jangling of electric bell ]
Anne: GOOD MORNING.
GOOD MORNING.
[ Clearing of throat ] GOOD MORNING.
[ Mixed whispers |]
GOOD MORNING, CLASS.
Girls: [ Snickering |.
REALLY, GIRLS,
IF YOU CAN'T COME UP WITH A BETTER LIKENESS THAN THAT,
| SUGGEST YOU GIVE UP ALTOGETHER.
OPEN YOUR OXFORD BOOK OF VERSE, PAGE 223.
TENNYSON'S "THE LADY OF SHALOTT".
EMMELINE, WOULD YOU PLEASE READ THE FIRST FOUR VERSES FOR US?
THEN WE'LL DISCUSS THEM.
My: MY, MY,
WHOSE APPLE ARE WE POLISHING NOW?
LET'S HITCH OUR WAGON TO A STAR, GIRLS.
Girls: [ Giggling |.
WILLOWS WHITEN, ASPENS QUIVER.
LITTLE BREEZES DUSK AND SHIVER.
THROUGH THE WAVE THAT RUNS FOREVER,
FLOWING DOWN TO CAMELOT.
[ Opening of door |.
WHY ARE YOU LATE?
MY MOTHER INSISTED ON KEEPING MY MAID THIS MORNING.
| HAD NO ONE TO DARN MY STOCKINGS.
KINGSPORT LADIES' COLLEGE DOES NOT TOLERATE TARDINESS,
NOR DOI.
TAKOUT YOUR DICTIONARY,
AND COPY OUT THE ENTIRE "A" SECTION.
YOU WILL HAVE TO CATCH UP ON THIS CLASS LATER.
THERE SHE KEPT HER VIGIL ONLY,
WAITING IN HER CHAMBER LONELY,
AND LOOKED DOWN TO CAMELOT.
REAPERS REAPING FIELDS OF BARLEY...
ARE YOU TRYING TO TELL ME THAT EMMELINE
IS SOLELY RESPONSIBLE FOR THIS MISCONDUCT?
| AM NOT TRYING TO TELL YOU ANYTHING
OTHER THAN THAT YOUR DAUGHTER
HAS AN OVERT DISREGARD FOR REGULATIONS.
STEALING IS STEALING.
| DON'T SEE H YOU CAN PRETEND IT TO BE OTHERWISE.
THIS INCIDENT IS THE TIP OF THE ICEBERG.
| BELIEVE SHE REQUIRES REMEDIAL DISCIPLINE.
|WANT THAT TEACHER RAKED OVER THE COALS AS WELL THEN.
I'D LIKE NOTHING BETTER, CAPTAIN HARRIS,
BUT THAT WILL BE FOR THE BOARD TO DECIDE.
LET ME BE PERFECTLY CLEAR, MISS BROOKE.
| WILL NOT ALLOW EMMELINE...
TO BE EXPELLED FROM ANY SCHOOL.
| AM WITH-DRAWING BOTH MY DAUGHTER
AND MY FINANCIAL SUPPORT FROM THIS SECOND-RATE INSTITUTION...
IMMEDIATELY.
YOU CAN RECKON WITH THE OARD OF GOVERNORS.
THERE SHE WEAVES BY NIGHT AND DAY,
A MAGIC WEB OF COLOURS GAY.
SHE HAS HEARD A WHISPER SAY,
"CURSES ON HER IF SHE STAY
TO LOOK DOWN ON CAMELOT?
Myra/Jen: [ Giggling |
| HAVE WARNED YOU TWO ABOUT FOOD IN CLASS.
BRING THAT PARCEL HERE, MYRA.
BRING THAT PARCEL HERE.
THROW IT IN THE STOVE.
ARE YOU SURE YOU REALLY WANT ME TO DOTHIS?
MYRA, OBEY ME AT ONCE.
Girl: WHY IS SHE RUNNING?
[| Screaming |.
RUN, GIRLS!
GIRLS, RUN!
[| Screaming |.
RUN, GIRLS!
Essie: NO!
RUN!
MY SKIRT IS CAUGHT.
[ Moan of fainting |]
Girls: [| Screaming |
[ Coughing |]
Captain Harris: EMMELINE!
PAPA! PAPA!
PAPA, YOU CAME.
MARCH STRAIGHT OUT TO THE CAR, YOUNG LADY, AND...
AND TAKE OFF THOSE RIDICULOUS-LOOKING SPECTACLES.
YOU SHOULDN'T BE WEARING THEM, OTHER THAN FOR READING.
[ Jangling of electric bell ]
Miss Brooke: SHUT THAT BLASTED ALARM BELL OFF.
THIS IS MY TEACHER, MISS SHIRLEY.
Captain Harris: MISS SHIRLEY, IS IT?
WE'VE MET BEFORE, IF 'M NOT MISTAKEN.
YES, SIR, | REMEMBER.
[ Soft moan ]
COME ON, ESSIE.
WHAT IN THE DEVIL HAVE YOU DONE NOW?
Captain Harris: MISS SHIRLEY'S GOT THE ENTIRE ACADEMY.
AWAITING YOUR REMEDIAL DISCIPLINE, MISS BROOKE.
I'M QUITE POSITIVE YOU'LL ENJOY THE CHALLENGE.
EMMELINE, COME ALONG.
YOU'RE LEAVING THIS FOURTH-RATE INSTITUTION ONCE AND FOR ALL.
[ Sigh of exasperation |.
Miss McKay: GIRLS, GIRLS, GET AWAY FROM THAT AUTO CAR.
(music)
What sort of things are being said!
Well, Hattie Pringle; You are accused of 'marking down'
her papers just because she Is a Pringle.
Here you are said to laugh at the students
when they make mistakes.
What?
Well alright | did laugh when Myra Pringle defined
an alligator as "a large kind of insect".
| couldn't help myself.
Oh dear.
Mr. James Pringle, the father of Jen Pringle claims that there
is no discipline whatsoever at the school since your arrival
"and he is circulating a report that you are a'Foundling."
Well, it goes on and on.
Almost every Pringle parent has written the Board demanding,
not requesting, demanding your resignation.
Oh those cantankerous, prejudiced old creatures!
How can anyone possibly succeed against such tactics!
I'm so sorry Anne.
| do feel responsible...
Well, on behalf of the 15 students who aren't Pringles
lam determined to persevere.
Captain Harris has withdrawn his rather substantial financial
support towards the college mortgage and several of the
other Pringle families are threatening to do the same
| see,
So you want me to resign as well.
Never.
The Board wants you to resign.
| want you to stay here and make these Pringles eat their words.
If money is deemed to be the power behind this institution,
well then you my dear Anne, are going to compensate for every
single penny that's been lost.
But how?
Shall | give up my salary?
Oh no my dear.
Oh no, no, no
lam going to insist that the Board give you a probationary
term at least until Christmas.
In the meantime might you consider mounting a lavish
benefit concert?
Highlighting a play perhaps directed by Miss Anne Shirley...
It will have to be something with a number of superb roles
in it though.
And strong dramatic content.
The audience will have to be completely overwhelmed.
| think every Pringle parent would gladly pay to see their
daughter's names in the program, don't you think!
Let's see uh, 100 tickets at $25 a ticket why that makes
exactly $2500...
That's an outrageous price!
Do you honestly think anyone would pay for that?
Yes, and all the money will go directly to the school.
You are perfectly ingenious Miss Stacey.
We'll show the Pringles the meaning
of the word "capitalism".
Justa minute Anne, | think that you should have
a look at these old diaries.
Mrs. Stanton, our librarian, and | are preparing a history
of Kingsport and we literally stumbled across
those in the archives.
They were written by Captain Abraham Pringle
the founder of Kingsport.
My dear Anne, if you want to win the game
you have to understand the players.
"| see.
"And so, for the last time the old teacher passed by the cruel
portrait of herself etched in the wall by her former students.
Gertrude glimpsed the old woman's haughty loneliness
as she retreated silently into the garden.
Shortly thereafter they learned that the hand of death
had touched her.
And Gertrude was haunted by the realization that she could
never thank the woman who had silently given her so much.
It was more than she could bear".
At this point in the term | would like to dedicate this
short story to each of you young ladies who have made
the first few weeks here for me so meaningful.
Class dismissed.
What are these girls crying for?
I've been reading them a short story, Miss Brooke.
Good grief - crying over an English lesson!
Miss Brooke is here to discuss my suggestion of a play
and benefit concert.
| think it's scandalous, but my opinion matters little
since the school needs the funds.
Exactly.
| was hoping you would assist me in the coaching, Miss Brooke.
| don't know why you would.
Since | had nothing to do with drawing up
this ridiculous scheme!
The most important question is, then, who shall play the leading
role of Mary Queen of Scots?
| think - We don't want any green horn in the role.
I'm not going to be associated with anything
that isn't successful.
Jen Pringle is the only one! Can think of who could
play the part.
No one else has the necessary personality.
| can't deny that Jen has a natural flair for acting.
Then it's all settled.
Why, | think Miss Brooke will make an excellent coach.
And Miss MacKay and Miss Kerr can do the decorations
and I'll see to the hiring of the hall and the band.
Perhaps | can even entice a famous soprano from Fredericton
to sing between acts at no charge!
| trust she'll sing for the creditors
if the whole thing flops!
But, don't say | didn't warn you!
Make your brush stroke move like furious fire, furiously.
Shoot out!
Make great big stitches so they won't show.
| implore you!
Don't just stand there like limp rags...
Help me, help me.
Feel it, feel it!
Let go the Queen.
Myra, you're using you upstage hand.
You're hiding your face.
Help me my mistress, have mercy.
Mercy nay | am innocent.
Save me sweet lady.
Will ye slay save me too?
Drag him away, pluck his hands off her.
This scene looks ridiculous.
Lam not gonna lower myself any further.
Hattie youre as stiff as a poker!
| can't help it.
| don't want to bruise myself.
If |can go down easily, | will.
You've all seen Essie carrying on.
Now do it this way.
Lam innocent, Save me sweet lady.
Oh!
..now the Queen she orders the guards to halt.
But the guards drag Rizzio away.
Now Hattie, you try it.
Lam innocent, save me sweet lady uh huh, uh huh.
| refuse to play opposite her.
Well, she is the only one who can be remotely convincing
as an Italian musician.
Do what you can Miss Brooke.
Well, don't blame me if the audience leaves.
Once more Hattie, and please relax!
Emmeline!
What is it, what ts it?
We've missed having you in our play.
Oh, I'm so sorry about what happened with your father.
Once everything's calmed down I'm hoping | can get a chance
to speak with him and try to explain.
He isn't here.
He's gone back to Boston.
Oh, Miss Shirley, I've always wanted to do a play...
I've never had much of a chance to do anything.
Papa will never let me come back to this school.
Lam to spend the rest of the year with grandmama, alone.
Oh Emmeline...
Perhaps | can get another copy of the play.
I'll coach you at home, if you like.
I'm sure your father will let you come back
to college next term.
| don't think so.
| don't think grandmama will either.
| had to sneak out while she and Aunt Pauline were napping.
Is someone helping you along with your studies?
You don't want to fall behind.
Well, then | shall have to have a chat with your Grandmama.
Will you?
You should hurry along home.
You don't want to get her cross.
And | promise | will come by tomorrow
and | will speak with her.
Oh, it's number 10 Mapple Terrace.
You won't forget...
Of course not.
Off you go.
Yes?
| should like to speak with Mrs. Harris.
My name is - You can't.
She is ill and won't be disturbed.
Good day.
May | speak with Emmeline Harris, then?
She isn't allowed to have visitors.
Is Captain Harris coming back to - Lives in Boston miss.
Seldom visits here.
Could you tell Emmeline that Anne Shirley came to see her?
Thank you.
My Dear Mrs. Harris: | thought you might be interested in these
diaries belonging to Captain Abraham Pringle, which | found
in the City Archives.
There are some wonderful tributes in here by Captain.
Pringle to your late husband, Captain Harris.
| hope you enjoy reading them as much as | did.
Sincerely, Anne Shirley, Kingsport Ladies College.
| have a delivery for Miss Shirley.
Well you're in luck.
Lam Miss Shirley.
Thank you.
So then it's tomorrow at noon ts it Mrs. Harris...
Miss Shirley Madam.
Mama.
Mama...
Good grief girl youre aggravating!
Miss Shirley.
What?
Miss Shirley!
Saints alive, why didn't you say so in the first place?
So, this is the infamous Miss Shirley.
Come to take her pound of flesh...
How do you do Mrs. Harris?
Far from well.
How much do you want for these diaries?
| hadn't any Intention of selling them.
Is there any use in asking you to sit down?
Yes
thank you.
Who else has seen these?
No one as far as | know.
Then I'm ready to negotiate.
| will give you what you want if you give me your word not
to reveal this monstrosity to the rest of the Pringles.
| was only hoping | might convince you to let me tutor
your granddaughter Emmeline as | understand
that she will not be returning to school.
Oh clever aren't we?
Sugarcoated blackmail!
You want a regular salary to keep you quiet, is that it?
| beg your pardon?
Innocent as doves, cunning as serpents.
You knew when you found that scandalous entry
about my husband it wasn't true.
| couldn't be true!
The rest of the Pringles will be dee-lighted
to believe it won't they?
And make us the laughing stock of Kingsport!
Which scandalous entry?
Oh, so there's more than one, is there?
Pauline.
Josiah Harris' ship was burned and their boats taken.
Harris and the crew nearly starved.
In the end they They ate Jonas Selkirk who had shot himself
they lived on him until rescued.
Harris told me himself.
Seemed to think it was a good joke.
On occasion papa would get so angry he'd...
Pauline!
Be quiet!
That is a lie.
My husband never ate anyone dead or alive.
Let alone Jonas Selkirk.
Abraham Pringle wrote that nonsense
to get a rise out of his silly wife.
Amy Pringle was notoriously gullible.
Oh, please Miss Shirley, don't show these to anyone.
Our Pringle relations might publicize it.
We'll do anything!
Ow.
Now Miss Shirley.
How much do you want to 'tutor my granddaughter?
Oh you've misunderstood me completely.
I'm not threatening you!
| just thought you'd enjoy all the other splendid things
said about your husband.
| never dreamed of telling anyone he was a cannibal.
Well naturally we tend to be a little suspicious of strangers
in Kingsport, perhaps we have misjudged you.
| suppose the child should continue with her studies.
Pauline has no time.
She's busy looking after me.
You won't mention this misunderstanding
to anyone will you?
I'll try to remember not to...
And when do you want to start?
Immediately.
Oh.
If two angles in a triangle are equal to each other, the two
sides opposite these two angles are equal to each other.
Emmeline, why hasn't anyone replaced your spectacles?
Well, papa says | don't really need to wear them
as much as | do.
And Grandmama won't because she's an old skin-flint!
Who gave you those, then?
Mother Superior at the convent in Boston two years ago.
Anyway, I'm only supposed to use them for reading.
You simply cannot use them anymore.
You must have another pair!
| found another copy Mary queen of Scots!
Oh, her very name just thrills me to my fingertips!
| don't believe she really murdered Darnley, do you?
Shh!
Heaven help you if you wake her up!
| think it's ever so dramatic, don't you?
It's a very challenging role.
We used to have dramatics and music at the convent.
Mother superior said | was quite good at both.
She taught me to play the piano too, you know.
Unfortunately, Grandmama won't let me touch it.
Could we read it together?
| think so.
I'll play all of the other parts and you read Mary.
Let's start here.
"Forgive all evil toward me of all men,
deed or device to hurt me."
Yea, | would not bear one heart unreconciled with mine
when mine is cold.
| will not take death's hand with any soil of hate or wrath
or wrong about me but being friends with this past world
pass from it in the general peace of love.
That was wonderfull!
Thank you for bringing me here, Miss Shirley.
This will be our secret place, which you
cannot reveal to anyone.
Grandmama never lets me out alone.
She thinks I'm liable to be "kidnapped by gypsies".
| don't know why she'd care if | was kidnapped.
All she worries about is her aching back and her sore feet.
Now, now.
Old people cling to the way they were brought up themselves.
Secretly she hates me.
She always calls me "the child"
as though | may be "the dog" or "the cat".
If | make a spark of noise she nearly passes out.
She's an old tyrant and someday I'm going to run away forever
and become a real actress.
Why have you never lived with your father?
He's very occupied with his business affairs.
| was at two other boarding schools before | came to this
one, but he brought me here... so I'd be close to Grandmama.
And so he wouldn't have to worry about me.
I'm sure he means to do what's best.
What Jen Pringle said about Papa
hurt you know... because it's true.
"Dear papa. | want so much to return to KLC."
No - | would like to ask you to allow me to go back
to KLC next term.
| was at the top of class before | left.
I'd hoped you'd be proud of my grades.
Please understand it was alla mistake.
| tried to reach you in Baltimore, but | suppose
"you never received the letter."
Miss Shirley is here for your tutorial, Miss.
Thank you.
Miss Shirley!
Grandmama will eat you alive.
If we are to have our studies in this room,
| simply cannot tolerate the gloominess any longer.
| have a wonderful surprise for you.
Miss Stacey has lent mea Royal Conservatory programme,
and you can begin today!
| can't.
Grandmama has forbidden me to touch...
Fiddlesticks!
It's high time someone reminded your Grandmama
what a piano sounds like...
And it shouldn't be me.
You can start with these elementary exercises
as a refresher course.
You will be on your own though, but it's a step
in the right direction.
I'll get your textbooks.
Play!
Pauline, come here gir!!
We will answer and we will tell them we cannot accept.
Mama wants her stationary Abigail.
Who on earth is making that confounded racket?
That piano isn't meant to be played!
Get away from there, child!
Who gave you permission to play that piano?
I'm sorry Mrs. Harris, but Emmeline must be allowed
to devote some time to musical studies.
| don't believe in young girls playing the piano in public.
It tends to make them bold and forward.
Why, | think perhaps you are wise Mrs. Harris.
However, I'm told that most of the young Pringle girls in.
Kingsport have private lessons.
Oh?
You just wouldn't want to be accused of negligence in.
Emmeline's proper upbringing?
No.
Who gave you permission to open those windows?
| just wanted your staff to see how dusty this room is.
It needs a thorough going over.
Well, have it your way.
You young people are all so giddy!
Pauline wants to go away and leave me.
It's only for the day Mama.
Only for a day says she!
It doesn't seem to occur to anyone that I'd like a day out
of this confounded wheelchair.
You may not have the use of your legs Grandmama,
but there's nothing the matter with your tongue.
Don't you dare to be impertinent child.
| know a girl died in her sleep after being impertinent.
Pauline, what Is it?
Uh, my cousin Louisa is celebrating her wedding
anniversary in Fredericton next week, and | was her bridesmaid
fifteen years ago, and I'd do anything to be there.
Well, if | die alone, while you're away, Pauline,
| leave it to your conscience.
| Know what a burden |! Can be.
Mama please don't excite yourself.
I'm not going to go if you're not willing.
| will excite myself.
Can't | have a little excitement to brighten my dull life...
Oh, oh my back, my back it hurts... close that confounded
window girl!
| feel the draft, Pauline get my afghan and a cushion
for my feet.
Well, you know how people will talk Mrs. Harris if Pauline
doesn't go to the anniversary?
What?
Oh, I'm sure in your long lifetime you've learned
what idle tongues can Say.
Well there's no need to throw my age up in my face, girl.
Oh, this town is full of tattering toadies
and don't | know it!
I'm not stopping her.
| left it to her own conscience.
No one will ever believe that excuse.
Miss Shirley and | can even stay with you, Grandmama.
Why, Pauline could probably be there and back in a day!
There's something behind all this isn't there?
Why are you all so set on her going?
Because she's a good kind daughter who needs a day off
now and then.
Never mind your wheedling ways.
Have a peppermint.
Oh... Oh my head.
Oh I've got such a pain In my head and I'm so tired
| can't argue anymore.
| suppose that means | am going to have a stroke.
Oh.
Alright you can go.
But if you catch flu and get sick don't blame me.
Oh thank you Mama, thank you.
You're so good to me!
| wanted to go to cousin Louisa's so much.
Mama...| only have this old black taffeta to wear.
Do you think...
Black taffeta Is quite good enough
for Louisa Hilton's wedding.
She'd go dressed in scarlet that one if | let her,
and only waiting till I'm dead to do it.
As long as I'm alive you will be decent Pauline Harris.
Alright Mama.
I'm just going to be glad inside and not even
think about what I'm wearing.
And I'm sure you'll get along
with Miss Shirley splendidly Mama!
| will not take death's hand with any soil of hate or wrath
or wrong about me, but being friends with this past world,
pass from it in the general piece of love...
Well you've all done remarkably well
and deserve multitudes of praise.
Now make sure you have your lines down pat
for next Friday's rehearsal.
Uh and before you go | have one announcement to make.
Mrs. Captain Josiah Harris and her granddaughter Emmeline,
would be pleased to invite you ladies
to a fall picnic tomorrow morning.
Now if you care to attend we will be meeting
at Maplehurst at 10:00am.
Please bring a small gift for Mrs. Harris out of politeness
for her generosity in hosting this event.
You can go home now girls.
It's coming.
It's coming...
They look wonderful.
Quite a reaction from those old diaries, Anne.
Goes to show you how my old students always pull through.
Don't speak too loudly yet!
| just received a letter from Gilbert Blythe.
Seems he's finally in medical school.
| know.
Well, how's he doing?
Well, you know Gilbert's so modest, but a - reading between
the lines I'd say he's at the top of his class.
He wanted to know how you're doing as well.
Well, you may tell him I'm keeping out of mischief.
Come in.
It's only me, Pauline.
Oh, Miss Shirley, how do | look?
Dreadful.
You simply cannot go in that old thing.
Lam gonna lend you my best dress.
Oh my dear, no, no, no...
I'm on tenterhooks as it is.
Mama might change her mind.
Oh, don't be silly.
Get up.
Take this black taffeta off
you can put this on underneath and can change at the party.
But to deceive mama!
You wouldn't want to bring bad luck to a wedding anniversary.
In this black thing would you?
No.
Hmm.
Oh! Ohl!
Oh, now just a whiff!
Mama won't approve of this.
Oh, apple blossom!
Oh how this reminds me of Adelaide Pringle when she...
Who?
Morgan's wife.
The mother of the child.
She was my first cousin on Mama's side.
| see,
Pauline why does your brother never visit?
Oh, Morgan, he's become just like Papa.
Always ordering people about.
No time for anyone else.
Morgan used to be so robust and handsome and Adelaide used
to love music and parties.
What happened?
Well, it's not Christian to speak of the dead.
Well, how did she die then?
She ran off shortly after the child was born.
And died of consumption.
The Pringles all blamed Morgan, including Mama.
But it wasn't Morgan's fault.
Now Mama won't have anything about that reminds her
of what happened to Adelaide.
That's wrong Pauline.
What makes the people in this town hold such grudges
against one another?
Oh the Pringles have always bickered
a great deal amongst themselves.
We're very polite to each other in public, though.
I've never seen such ridiculous behaviour.
It's absolutely Byzantine!
Well, in any case Pauline Harris, you are going to have
the 'day off' of your life.
Good morning, Mrs. Harris.
Walking as if we owned the world are we?
So | do.
Come along Pauline!
|...' m ready to go Mama.
Too much colour girl.
You look painted.
Oh no.
It's just I'm flushed.
Well you don't smell respectable drenched in scent.
It's just the tiniest... little... bit of it.
| said drenched and | meant drenched.
Turn around.
Is that a rip under that sleeve?
Uh... no.
Oh, remember your manners and don't forget to cross your
ankles decently when you sit down.
And don't sit in a draft either.
And don"t slide down the banisters.
Mama!
Well you did at Nancy Pringle's wedding.
Mama, that was 25 years ago.
What do you think | am?
Go on girl.
Don't stand there jabbering.
Do you want to miss your train?
No, Mama.
And if I'm not here when you come back, remember,
lay me out in my wedding dress.
And mind my hair is crimped!
| don't know how you'll manage her Miss Shirley.
She's such a baby.
| never thought I'd ever get a chance to visit Maplehurst.
Ettie, Ettie Pringle get away from there,
that's Mrs. Harris' carriage.
This is outrageous.
| haven't been outside...
If | catch cold girl, | Shall hold you responsible.
Nonsense!
| want you to enjoy the sunshine
and all the beautiful autumn colours.
We'll have a lovely carriage ride and you can criticize
everyone we pass by!
Criticize?
That's a very strange idea Miss Shirley.
That's not Christian.
It's simply not Christian.
What is the meaning of this!
Miss Shirley, | won't stand for anymore of your monkeyshines!
You have such handsome Carriages and never use them.
You put them back do you hear!
They've not been out for seven years!
All the more reason to bring them out and use them.
Stop being so selfish.
Good morning girls.
You look lovely!
You bring me back in!
Do you hear?
This is anarchy!
Who are these rabble-rousers?
Oh dear saints above | shall swoon.
| can't stand all this fresh air.
It's such a pretty day, | thought you could host
a picnic for the school.
| don't eat my lunch outside with anyone girl.
I'm not a raggle-taggle gypsy.
Take me in! Take me in!
Hush now, Mrs. Harris; Some of these young girls are Pringles.
Pringles?
Yes.
And you don't want them running home and telling tales.
You'll pay for this.
If | catch a chill...
You said you wanted a day off from your
wheelchair anyway Grandmama.
Be quiet!
Good morning Mrs. Harris.
You look awfully chipper.
Thank you Alec McGuinness.
Thank you.
Well, what does it matter if | die anyway?
I've been living on borrowed time for too long as it is.
Such friendly people!
Charming neighbours.
You know | don't approve of your criticizing people my dear.
May | ask is that all your own hair.
Yes.
Every bit.
Pity it's red.
But | believe red is becoming quite popular again.
Thank you.
And another one?
How delightful!
Now, thank you my dear.
This is my gift to you, Emmeline.
Oh, Miss Shirley!
However did you pay for this?
| had some lucky savings put aside.
Oh!
Thank you a million times over!
Some day I'll make it up to you!
Now wasn't that sweet of all these girls to give me gifts?
Yes, it was.
Yes, | rather like your laugh Miss Shirley.
That nervous giggle of Pauline's it gets on my nerves.
Well, | hope she has a wonderful time at the party.
She's probably over eaten and made herself ill.
Like her father, that girl.
Course, he never knew when he'd had enough.
Did | ever show you Josiah's picture, Miss Shirley?
He was very handsome.
Full of heroic spirit, I'd say.
Yes.
He was the handsomest man in Kingsport.
And he adored me.
We consulted each other about absolutely everything.
Mind you, we didn't always agree - no.
He had his fits of temper.
Oh yes, and so did I.
You know what he did when | bought a day-cap he didn't like?
| can't imagine...
He ate It!
Gave him a terrible stomach pain!
Yes, served him right.
He was so irked that | had neglected to consult him!
How could he go away and leave me alone and crippled like this?
Dying was the only thing he ever dared do without consulting me.
Well, it won't be long before we're together again.
There's no one... no man... like him... nowhere... no.
This is a degenerate age, Miss Shirley.
What about your son?
Morgan.
Oh, well he managed his money successfully
if that's any merit.
His father spoiled him.
No, he should never have married his cousin.
It was a blessing that poor Adelaide Pringle died dear soul;
Morgan got what he deserved | suppose.
That's a very inhuman attitude for a mother, Mrs. Harris.
Yes, well we're not exactly famous for compassion.
Miss Shirley, especially among ourselves.
Anyway they're all waiting for me to die
so they can get their hands on the money.
Perhaps you ought to realize that Emmeline only wants
to be cared for.
Well.
If you have any compassion left in your soul,
you might spend it on her.
Children should be seen and not heard.
You seem to be very broad-minded in your opinions Miss Shirley.
That's the nicest compliment anyone's
ever paid me Mrs. Harris.
Pardon me young man, | was wondering if you would allow my
girls and me the pleasure of a hayride to town in your wagon.
It would be so exciting, but | promise you...
Mama, Mama!
You'll simply have to go.
Good-bye.
Mama, Mama.
What's happened?
Mama are you alright?
You're wearing a hat.
Mama | can't remember the last time you wore a hat.
Pauline will you calm yourself.
You sound hysterical.
You've seen me wear a hat often enough girl.
Miss Shirley suggested an Al Fresco lunch
it was most enjoyable.
I've been so anxious about you mama.
| was worried sick the entire party.
Will you stop fluttering girl!
You fidget me.
Pauline, did you have a good time at your wedding party?
Oh my yes.
Oh, Louise sent you her bouquet Mama.
The flowers were wonderful.
The parlour was a bower...
Like a funeral | suppose...
And the minister married Cousin Louise and Maurice over again.
Sacrilegious...
And Molly and Emily send their love.
Oh and Emily has the most delicious baby.
You speak as though it was something to eat.
Babies are common enough.
Babies are never Common.
Each one is a miracle.
Well | had two of them.
| didn't see much that was miraculous about either of them.
Mama you're so bright and cheerful today.
However did you two get along Miss Shirley?
| let her have her head and we got on well enough.
| don't care what the Pringles say...
| think you're quite good looking.
Thank you.
Oh good grief!
Well, well.
Little Bo Peep has lost her sheep and doesn't
know where to find them.
Good day Miss Kerr.
After this | shall be Surprised at nothing.
Leave them alone and they'll come home bringing
their tails behind them.
Get those sheep and that wagon out of here!
Papa!
Emmeline you were told to stop wearing those ridiculous
spectacles outside.
Your eyesight will never improve if you constantly wear them.
Yes Papa.
But Miss Shirley gave me these new ones and...
Go inside.
| mean immediately.
But...
Hurry up.
Young man whose fault is this?
Is this your wagon?
Thank you.
We had a marvellous time.
Miss Shirley...
May | have a word with you?
You run along, Miss Kerr.
Il catch up.
Yes, Sir.
It seems that each time we meet catastrophe lies in my way.
Well then perhaps you ought to get out of the way.
| get annoyed when people treat my instructions lightly,
Miss Shirley.
| gave explicit order that my daughter was to have no further
association with Kingsport Ladies College.
Would you mind telling me what the devil you're doing here?
We've been ona country picnic, sir.
Hosted by your mother.
My mother?
She authorized taking out all of those carriages
and inviting all those girls?
NO SIV.
| did.
And as she had nothing better to think about than herself,
| felt it was high time someone tried to help her.
Then you really are as insane as
all the rumours I've heard about you.
What have you heard?
You wouldn't want to know.
Yes | would!
The Pringles have labeled you the madcap English professor.
Someone said you had written the most ridiculous story they had
ever read published by... uh... something or other.
Reliable Baking Powder Company?
And that you were the silliest, redheaded,
mouse of a schoolmistress they'd ever known.
Thanks to you, | was very nearly fired!
There's a logical explanation behind everything, but you
people really are the most narrow-minded, self-centred,
quarrelsome group | have ever encountered!
I'd like to poison your entire clan!
You can't stand to see anyone succeed other than yourselves.
Oh, I'm sure you're all gloating over who will fly the victory
banner at the end of this year!
Well, you have not got the better of me yet!
Whoa, whoa.
Come back here.
You're upset by what the Pringles think of you?
| don't care to discuss it, if you don't mind.
I'm sorry.
You're afraid the Pringle rumours might reinforce
my conclusions about you...
Your conclusions?
Don't flatter your self!
You might be interested in listening to what | actually
had to say in your defence!
You ought to look around and see if there's anyone
you would like to listen to better than yourself!
| took it upon myself to see that this was delivered to you.
I'm sure you're far too busy to forward a change of address
to your daughter.
If you weren't so self-absorbed, sir, you'd realize there's
a little girl who desperately loves you.
You can go.
Morgan!
Miss Shirley!
Wait!
Morgan, I'll be right back.
Miss Shirley!
Oh, Miss Shirley, thank goodness you didn't let mama see me
getting out of that fellow's carriage!
Pauline, you're positively trembling!
Oh! It was heavenly!
| simply have to tell you everything!
Isaac Kent drove me home!
He used to be an old beau of mine.
Well... no.
Hardly an old beau.
He never had any real intentions, but we used to
go driving round together.
He... ah... he... paid mea compliment.
He said'
"your hair looks as mush like molasses taffy as it ever did."
| hope there wasn't anything improper in him saying that!
Nothing whatsoever!
OH.
He asked me to go driving again.
Heaven knows what mama's going to say, but...| don't even care!
Louisa and l... walked all around the old house.
Remembered all of the summers we had spent together as
girls... some of the lilac bushes that we planted years ago
| don't know... I've just never had such a wonderful day!
Pauline, I'm so pleased!
How can | ever repay you?
| just wish you didn't have such a difficult time here.
Oh, | don't even mind coming home, somehow.
Morgan's here for a few weeks on business.
| hope it will be just like old times.
Mama needs me.
And it's nice being needed, isn't it?
Oh!
Thank you, Miss Shirley!
You keep the dress.
Heaven knows, you might get to wear it again!
God bless you!
You've done more than you'll ever know!
Kingsport Ladies College, Miss Brooke Speaking.
Why good afternoon, Mrs. Pringle...
Sore throat?
Tonsillitis! Good heavens!
| hope it isn't serious... It's not contagious is it?
Oh | see...
No, no
but... no we understand completely.
One must not interfere with a doctor's orders.
| agree with you Mrs. Pringle.
| appreciate your giving us sufficient notice...
Thank you...
Good-bye.
Jen Pringle will not be performing this evening.
You can't be serious?
Not after all this effort.
We shall simply have to return the tickets and put it off.
Until when?
We can't afford to re-book the hall.
And what about the band?
| still have to pay for them.
Well Muriel Stacey | told you it was foolish to get up a play
this time of year.
Don't blame me.
Jen Pringle is in no more danger of tonsillitis than | am.
This is a deliberate device to ruin the play
to try and get rid of me.
That's an awfully sour attitude!
What do you intend to do?
Read it yourself?
That would ruin it... Mary is the entire play!
We are not postponing anything.
I'll be back in an hour.
Carry on as we planned until you hear from me.
Miss Shirley.
| would like to speak to Captain Harris, please.
Lam sorry he's busy in the study.
And | regret to say he won't be disturbed
lam sorry Annabel; But this is a matter
that goes beyond regret.
Come in!
I'll look at the shipment in Boston.
On Monday.
Alright.
| apologize for interrupting you so rudely Sir.
Ll be brief.
Because you've withdrawn your financial support from the.
College, we have been attempting to raise the balance of our
operating costs through the production of a benefit concert
scheduled for this evening.
Now our concert is threatened because Jen Pringle, our leading
performer has called in ill at the last minute.
Emmeline knows the part cold, we've been studying it together.
This opportunity would mean everything to her.
| Know what you think of me, my methods and the school!
But, | beg of you to let her perform with us tonight.
| take it then you job is on the line?
I intend to see this through, Sir.
You had no business interfering here, Miss Shirley.
Emmeline is far too easily influenced for her own good.
But under the circumstances l
| feel lowe you an apology for some of the things | said
the other day and for the trouble I've obviously caused.
| meant no harm.
Please.
That was my own fault.
Perhaps | reacted hastily taking Emmeline out of school.
Pringles like to throw their weight around this community.
You might say | took Emmeline's expulsion
as an attack on myself.
But ll
| thought you supported the general consensus.
Please...
Don't lump me in with that lot.
Kingsport Is a very insidious town.
Lam grateful to you for your insights, Miss Shirley.
Emmeline may go.
Emmeline may go?
Oh.
Thank you Sir, I'm just dizzy with gratitude.
Sorry...
Miss Shirley, Miss Shirley.
You and Emmeline hurry along.
The Pringles will be sharpening their knives.
Thank you.
Forgive all evil toward me of all men Deed or device to hurt me.
Yea | would not bear one heart unreconciled With mine
when mine is cold | will not take death's hand With any soil
of hate or wrath or wrong about me, but being friends with this
past World, pass from it in the general peace of love...
Thank you.
Thank you all so much for your... well... overwhelming
support for this evening's benefit.
| would now like to introduce to you, KLC's brilliant,
young English professor.
An individual who has overseen every last inch of this
production and whose inspired direction has brought forth
such magnificent performances from your daughters.
Miss Anne Shirley!
Miss Shirley, on behalf of the King's County Board of.
Education, it gives me very great pleasure
to present you with this cheque.
The proceeds of this evening's exciting event made out to the.
Kingsport Ladies College in the amount of two thousand,
five hundred dollars!
Thank you ladies and gentlemen.
It would be impossible for me to speak without having by my side
the three other energetic supporters of tonight's event.
Miss Kerr, Miss MacKay, and especially our beloved
principal, Miss Katherine Brooke; Who have all worked so
tirelessly on this production.
It was with great trepidation that | began my year here
at Kingsport Ladies College.
And | owe an enormous debt of gratitude to my fellow teachers
and to the parents of my students who all tried to make
me feel so at home during my first few weeks in Kingsport.
| have grown to love and respect all of our girls at KLC
and have found many kindred spirits among them.
If we have opened your hearts this evening and entertained
you even a little, we have succeeded.
Thank you all for your very fine support.
| can't thank you enough for what you've done for my Myra.
She's gotten along better this term than she has
ina long time.
She's a... joy to teach!
Thank you!
| just hope they all realize what a jewel you are, my dear.
| know some of the other Pringles have been abominable,
but | don't care what they say.
You can board with me next term!
Thank you for the invitation!
| had a teacher just like you when | was a girl.
You brought back SO many memories!
Congratulations, my dear!
Thank you for your kind support.
Papa... Papa... What did you think?
You were an angel that stole away everyone's heart,
including mine.
Come back to earth now for a little while.
It all feels like a dream.
Thanks, I'm glad you enjoyed it.
Emmeline.
Oh, you were wonderful.
Thank you!
Looks like you single-handedly routed the entire Pringle clan.
Well, let's just say the winds of persecution have blown over.
Thank you, Sir.
This has meant a great deal to me.
I'll never forget it as long as live.
Nor will I.
Goodnight Emmeline.
Miss Shirley!
I'd like you to go on tutoring my daughter so she'll be
caught up when she returns to the college.
I'm prepared to make it worth your while.
Only if you put my wages back into supporting the college.
You're asking me to renegotiate.
Yes.
You have a deal!
Thank you!
Good night Emmeline.
Good night.
Miss Brooke generously left the light on for us!
She must be in a good mood!
Settle down.
I'll be along shortly to tuck you girls in.
Isn't that ring around the moon enchanting?
I've seen a good many moons in my time.
You haven't seen this one.
Sit down!
Let's let it just soak into our souls.
Wasn't it a marvellous evening?
Don't make a fool out of yourself, please.
It was thought in ancient times that when a man and a woman sat
under such a moon, they would be bonded together
in love for eternity.
Love... if | died tomorrow, not one living soul would miss me.
What is it you want, Anne Shirley?
To be your friend.
| don't have friends.
| don't have your notable gift for doing the queen act - always
saying the right thing to everyone.
You say you like people to be frank?
Well I'm going to be frank.
It's your own fault that no one likes you!
Katherine Brooke, you are all prickles and stings!
| know I'm unsocial and people hate me.
Do you think it doesn't hurt that I'm always neglected
and overlooked at social functions?
I'm sorry.
I've never been able to swallow all the snubs and pokes
I've received during my life.
| remember every single one.
For fifteen years | had to endure relatives who cared as
little for me as my dead parents!
| lived in third-rate boarding houses that froze in winter
and stank in summer!
I've worn their cast-off clothes!
Fortunately, | had my grades.
| made it through college and | paid back every cent!
Oh yes, I'm independent now.
The truth is, | hate teaching!
But there's nothing else | can do!
Look at you.
Little messenger of optimism.
But how long will it last?
Five?
Maybe ten years before you wither
inside of this... endless monotony.
Prepare to join the ranks of cold, uninteresting spinsters
who have chosen a professional career, Anne Shirley!
"and in particular, the performance of Emmeline Harris
who was So convincing in the role of the young queen.
The audience was so unexpectedly moved.
It is our opinion that this proficient group of young
actresses must establish a permanent dramatic society.
"The Kingsport Examiner eagerly awaits their next production."
And on that note of praise, | hope you all perform
as triumphantly on your term exam next Friday.
Class dismissed.
Emmeline!
I'd like to apologize... for the... inconvenience
that | caused you, Miss Shirley.
We're all glad to see that your health
has improved... so quickly.
Yes.
| think that the doctor was overly concerned.
| hope | may stay in the dramatic society - if you're
going to continue.
Oh. We couldn't do without you.
Oh, thank you, Miss Shirley!
Oh - my mother wants to know if you'd like to help
with the annual hospital bazaar.
If you have the time.
Tell your mother I'd be flattered!
Good afternoon girls.
Oh Anne.
Hello.
The Board was totally enthralled.
Better than that
they were absolutely floored when they received.
Captain Harris' cheque.
They want to renew your contract for five years!
Five years!
I'm not sure | could last that long.
Well, | think that you ought to write a book about it.
Oh Miss Brooke isn't it wonderful!
Authors are such kittle kattle.
| wouldn't trust your description of any of us.
Here, these came for you.
Thank you.
Oh!
Thank you again.
| would like to return the favour.
I'd be pleased to have you escort my family
for a short visit to Boston when | return in a month.
Sincerely, Morgan Harris.
Oh, they're beautiful!
Pauline Harris you don't know If you're coming or going girl.
Move that hatbox.
Not up there girl you'll brain me.
It's not safe up there either.
Put it back girl, put it back!
Lower the blind, it needs to be just about one inch lower.
Oh Pauline... Pauline.
Now you've done it!
All that light makes my headache worse.
I'm sorry Mama.
Well, you've got your colour back Mrs. Harris;
you must be feeling better.
Lam completely worn out with all the worry
and motion sickness.
My stomach is dropping out of me.
Why | ever listened to you and came on this trip
in the first place...
Now, now... we're almost there.
Perhaps you'd like some lunch Pauline.
We are not hungry.
Can they make a decent cup of tea on this contraption?
I'd rather drink mud than the tea that some people make.
Yes Mrs. Harris.
Il see what | can procure.
..and see that they wash the cup out properly.
| don't mean to be a trouble to anyone... but the way I'm feeling
| don't think I'll be here much longer.
Then perhaps you'll appreciate me.
Poor Aunt Pauline.
Oh well, grandmama will sleep for days once we get there.
| can hardly wait to see Papa's new house.
I've only ever heard of how wonderful it is.
I've a feeling we're all here on approval.
Papa thinks very highly of you, Miss Shirley.
He said so.
Hello, how is mother?
She allowed us to order her a cup of tea.
However, she Is throwing out complaints
at the speed of this train.
If we like your new house in Boston Papa,
can Miss Shirley and | stay with you?
Hmm, | don't know if Boston's large enough
for two sophisticated ladies.
Going from Avonlea to Kingsport was an adventure Captain.
| assure you this will be an epoch in my life.
Well, I'm sure you and Boston will make quite an impression
on each other.
If |can remember not to look as backward as | feel.
All this moving about
my neuritis is agony and nobody cares what | suffer.
Mother...
So this is what you've been wasting my money
on Morgan Harris.
| didn't invite you all the way to Boston to carry on like this!
It isn't fair, Morgan.
It simply isn't fair!
The child had got to come back and live with you!
| can't afford the expenses and | simply
can't stand the trouble!
Pauline has got quite enough to do - Oh, | don't mind mama.
Please don't contradict me!
Don't be so demanding!
She's back in school, besides | thought
you enjoyed having her with you!
Lam 79 years of age, my boy, and | can't be bothered
with the child.
You've got this enormous house!
It all comes out of your father's estate, doesn't it?
Huh?
| have every right to be 'demanding'!
Why don't you get married again?
| haven't the temperament for it.
| suppose no one would take you!
Mind your own business, mother!
Of course, | realize my opinions don't matter any longer.
| might just as well be dead.
Then you can have the rest of the money!
Please don't say that, mama - will say it!
You're two ungrateful children!
How many times have | sat up at night, nursing you?
When you were little?
Sometimes | thought you'd never live to see the dawn!
A mother's sacrifices are soon forgotten.
Mama.
Please come to bed.
It's just the strain of being.
Saints above, Pauline! Will you keep out of this?
Now listen to me, Morgan.
Lam not going to bed until you give me a decisive answer.
Face up to your responsibilities and behave like a man!
All right!
| shall look into making the arrangements as soon as | can.
Well.
That's better.
Goodnight?
Goodnight, Morgan.
You can't rely on that boy to stay in the same line for two
minutes together.
He'll toss that child back in my lap as sure as Sure can be.
And what do you think of my son's lack of responsibility?
| quite agree!
Goodnight, Miss Shirley!
Please... don't get up.
| just wanted to say what a lovely evening this has been.
And thank you for giving me such a wonderful opportunity.
| apologize for mother's behaviour.
In her condition, sarcasm is her one relief.
It's her Pringle nature
| suppose.
I'm surprised you've put up with all this Kingsport nonsense
as well as you have.
Well, it has been a challenge...
As well asa very good experience.
Oh, | desperately miss my Green Gables though.
Watching the home lights flicker across the pond
at night... Marilla waiting for me on the verandah.
Probably sounds very foolish to you.
Can't escape your wholesome Island upbringing...
It must feel very empty living in this vast house all alone.
Well, it's an investment really.
I'm away so frequently.
What is it that keeps you away from Kingsport?
Keeping occupied with the all-consuming problems
of my business.
Running away...?
No. Perhaps holding out for a reason to return.
Well, | hope you've found one.
I'm very grateful to you for all your hospitality.
Well, I'm very grateful to you for the pleasure
of such high spirits.
Goodnight.
Goodnight Morgan Harris.
Anne Shirley, | hope we shall see you often
when | return to Kingsport.
Let's try a new one, shall we?
Yes!
Do you think this makes me look older, papa?
Oh, yes, Emmeline.
We can't make up our minds which of these hats
look more sophisticated!
Neither can l.
We'll take all of them.
Papa!
Here she is.
The great lady of the West Indies.
She's magnificent!
What does "Mistral" mean, papa?
It means a "rough, cold wind".
Oh no, Captain.
It should be Christened after a delicious, perfumed wind.
Like a zephyr.
Then I shall name the next one the Zephyr in your honour!
..and the excursion to Boston all seems like a dream somehow.
Emmeline, who has had sucha forsaken life up to now
has blossomed and | feel Captain Harris now recognizes
the treasure he didn't know he possessed.
Lam a little weary of living out of a trunk though
and | long to feel the summer loveliness of home.
| miss you both so very much.
With all my heart.
Anne.
She's plain worn out if you ask me Marilla.
I'm not surprised, the way girls roam the earth now
is something terrible.
It reminds me of Satan in the Book of Job going to and fro
and walking up and down.
| don't think the Lord ever intended it...
What is to be will be Rachel.
And what isn't to be sometimes happens.
Riches are all very well Marilla.
But if Anne prefers the handsome unknown to Avonlea.
Well, there's nothing more to be said.
It's in the hands of Providence.
| enjoyed your company in Boston.
| hope the term is continuing well in Kingsport and Emmeline.
Is caught up now in her studies.
Thank you again.
Sincerely, Morgan Harris.
Anne Shirley.
What in heck are you doing here?
Gil?
You're the very last person I'd ever expected to meet out
here on a day like this!
C'mon.
The Royal Academy of Physicians is convening here this weekend
and I'm here as a delegate.
You must be proud of yourself.
Not as proud as | was of you when | read that clipping.
Miss Stacey sent me about the success of your play.
That's sweet of you Gil.
It's so good to see you.
Well | was actually hoping we'd run into each other.
| wasn't sure whether you'd be happy to see me or not, sol.
Happy?
| can't begin to express my happiness!
Let me look at you.
Oh yes.
Do | look like a young medical student now?
Not a bit.
You can't fool me.
You are still the same incorrigible Gil.
Tell me all the Avonlea news.
Have you been back?
Uh, no, I've been spending most of my time
with the Stuarts in Halifax.
Dr. Stuart's a very prominent surgeon.
It's he who arranged for me to attend as his delegate.
You see...
Christine and | are engaged.
It's set for next summer.
I'm so happy for you Gil.
| guess that's why | wanted to see you so much; To apologize
for being such a fool last summer.
You know, | think | understand now what you meant.
| meant what | said too and | won't ever forget you.
You turned out as | always imagined you would.
Doesn't it seem like yesterday we were off to Queen's
and vying for those scholarships.
| suppose you've kept up your writing.
Not really...
I've been busy and well Publishers aren't interested
in those kinds of stories.
Well | wouldn't give up altogether.
You know | always thought you should write a book
about Avonlea.
Change the name, of course, or Rachel Lynde would think
she was the heroine.
Avonlea is the dearest place in the world, | don't think
it's an interesting enough setting for a story.
Well, | intend to take Christine back to the Island with me
and set up my practice there.
Dr. Stuart has a lot of pull in Halifax and would like us
to live there, but | don't want any handouts.
Besides, any other place just wouldn't seem like home to me.
No, of course.
The Board of Governors at the college just offered
me a five-year contract...
That's wonderful.
You've certainly won your way into the hearts
of this affluent old town.
You won't be lonely.
I'll survive.
Well | ought to go.
Train leaves at 5:30.
Aw, no. Really?
Oh... Uh | was going to uh mail this but...
A note just isn't the same.
Thanks Gil.
Good-bye Anne.
Good-bye Gil.
Don't forget me.
Gill.
Thank you, Good-bye.
Good-bye Anne.
Miss Shirley would you help US arrange all these garlands
and bunting?
This is a hopeless mess!
What's the matter Mrs. Pringle?
Not one of these nitwits has as much artistic ability
you have in your baby finger.
Ladies I'm putting Miss Shirley in charge here.
Let me see.
| suggest you gather it up in a rosette like this
and then we'll hang them with the festoons afterwards.
We were all so impressed with your production
at the college Miss Shirley.
Thank you.
And to think how you transformed Morgan Harris' little girl.
He's hardly had anything to do with the poor child
since she was born.
Such a tragedy when his Adelaide died...
She was a rare beauty.
Old Mrs. Harris and mother Pringle are first cousins.
And | know how the Harrises have cut themselves off
from everybody.
It was Morgan's fault though, she ran away and left him.
Terrible reputation with the ladies.
They say Adelaide really died of a broken heart.
I'm sure that he's felt sO guilty all these years
that he can't stand the sight of the child.
More than likely it's the old lady he can't stand.
Well | know for a fact that he has been seeing Elvira Evans...
Standard Oil Fortune from Boston.
She has been staying for the last two weeks at Maplehurst
or so my sister-in-law tells me.
You've gotten to know Cousin Morgan haven't you Miss Shirley?
Yes.
We've met on several outings.
He's very charming.
We're going to give Miss Evans a tour of the old town this
afternoon, Emmeline.
"Dear Miss Shirley, please accept our congratulations
on your book entitled 'Avonlea Vignettes.
Enclosed is our cheque for two hundred and fifty dollars
"as advanced against Our royalties."
Anne!
Anne?
Oh, hello.
Anne, | was hoping I'd run in to you.
We've missed having you back at Maplehurst.
| can imagine it must be very difficult for you to get away
from your important guest.
Yes, it is.
But please.
Don't apologize. | understand.
Good day, Sir.
May | offer you a ride back to the college?
No, thank you.
What's nagging you, Miss Shirley?
You're behaving rather like a spinsterly old school marm,
don't you think?
Perhaps that's because | am one!
| say that with admiration!
That was a compliment.
Lam a great proponent of independent thinking.
Moreover, | have always held that early marriages are a sure
indication of second rate goods that had to be sold in a hurry.
Wouldn't you agree?
Well you can be sure | am of the first rate kind, Morgan Harris,
and | certainly have far greater ambitions than marriage.
All that you are insinuating is nagging me.
| about to have a short work of fiction published!
Lam afraid it has me completely occupied!
Well, let me offer my congratulations!
Good day!
Anne... Anne!
Lam sorry.
| ought not to have such a back handed invitation.
I've been meaning to ask mother to invite you back
to Maplehurst.
How gracious of you!
But my schedule is so jam packed, | am sure! Won't be
able to squeeze it in.
| take it you'll attend
the hospital benefit tomorrow evening?
Yes.
I'm working as a volunteer.
| shall look forward to seeing you there.
Would you do me the honour, Miss Shirley,
of reserving me waltz on your card.
Of course.
I'd be pleased to, Morgan Harris.
Thank you.
If | have a waltz space free!
Well, what do you think?
You look like a Gibson magazine cover!
Perhaps some romantic artist will fall for you
and ask to paint your picture...
Oh, miss Shirley!
'm gonna wear my hair just like that when | turn eighteen!
You darlings!
Imitation is the sincerest form of flattery.
Would you run along and see if my cab is here?
Thank you!
My, my... Going to London to visit the queen, are we?
Are you not capable of saying anything pleasant?
No.
| haven't your talent for pretending things.
You take my breath away with your compliments.
You always have some secret delight, don't you?
Don't deceive yourself!
You'll never be one of them!
Despite you flaunting your string of pearls and making
a spectacle of yourself.
Morgan Harris is aman of status and achievement.
And you, my dear, are nothing better than a teacher.
| don't know what you mean, but | honestly
feel sorry for you, Katherine.
You shut out every spark of happiness around you.
| will not be poisoned by your bitterness!
You are good luck Anne Shirley.
This is the largest number of tickets we've ever sold
for the hospital.
Well, | enjoy helping out any which way | can Mrs. Pringle.
Don't get stuck behind that table all night.
Be sure to get a dance.
| will.
You took the teacher's course at Queen's.
Shirley, isn't it?
Anne Shirley.
Yes.
Lewis Allen.
| remember you won the Avery scholarship
and Gilbert Blythe won the Gold Medal.
Yes that's right.
Pleased to know you.
What do you do now, Lewis?
I'm the principal of Richmond Public School.
Not the most adventurous place in the world, but uh I've done
alright for myself, compared to a lot of others from Queen's.
Do you dance as well as you boast?
Better.
Morgan Harris certainly upstaged the Pringles
with that Evans woman.
They say she's a perfect cat.
Worth millions though.
I've met her and believe me it will take all his gold
to gild a pill like her.
A match of adjoining bank accounts, to be sure.
Anne! Anne!
Good evening Sir; Or rather Goodnight.
Goodnight?
You promised me a waltz.
I'm sorry.
My card was full all evening.
You needn't feel obligated to patronize
the local schoolteacher.
I'm sure you've paid handsomely for your tickets.
Wait a moment, let me explain.
Please don't spoil the evening for your guest
by causing a scene.
Anne.
Where are you going?
I'm quite exhausted.
Please don't complicate matters by making excuses.
Elvira Evansisa business associate.
For the past year | have been liquidating the last of her
father's shipping estate.
Bringing her to Maplehurst was a gesture of hospitality.
The conclusion of a lengthy transaction.
| know when I'm being conveniently excluded.
It isn't that at all.
Be reasonable.
Why should I.
| have no ulterior motives.
You're acting as fickle-minded as a breeze.
We all go on about you.
Even Mother.
She absolutely adores you.
Under the circumstances how could | have invited you
this evening?
| certainly wasn't fishing for an invitation.
Perhaps it's my wholesome Island upbringing, but | have
no intention of becoming "fancy's fool"!
| would like you to come back to Maplehurst.
Indeed | don't know why.
As Emmeline's governess perhaps?
I'll save you the trouble of asking.
| won't lose you Anne Shirley.
Let go of me.
Please, | would... oh!
Morgan Harris, oh I'm awfully sorry, but you grabbed me.
| want to ask you to marry me.
What did you say?
I'm in love with you.
You really mean that don't you.
My life on it.
| only know | could never bear to lose you.
Would you do me the honour of giving me your hand in marriage?
Anne, what is it?
| do care a great deal for you and Emmeline.
But | can't.
What do you mean?
| mean that for five glorious seconds | really thought
perhaps | could marry you.
| used to dream of a moment like this.
Now, | can't describe it, |need to go home.
You could go back for summer holidays.
Rent one of those big old places on the Gulf.
Not the same thing
is it?
No.
Look at you.
You're out here without even your coat on!
You'll catch your death.
We should go back in.
| still have a waltz free.
Alright?
Let's give those old ladies something to gossip about.
Come in...
Why Mr. McGuinness, what is it?
You must come quickly to Maplehurst, Miss.
Everyone's worried.
Mrs. Harris has kept silent all week.
Silent?
Something must be dreadfully wrong.
She took a bad spell just after Papa left.
Now she won't eat or drink and poor Aunt Pauline is beside
herself to know what we should do.
Miss Shirley thank goodness you've come.
I'm afraid that she's slipping away,
and it's all my fault.
Isaac Kent wants me to... to... marry
him... practically.
He's asked me to join the Presbyterian Church
choir league.
Mama hates Isaac as much as she did fifteen years ago when she
set the bull terrier on him for coming around to see me.
| don't think she'll forgive me.
I'm so afraid she's going to die...
You must choose between them, Pauline.
Oh, | don't think | can live without him!
Don't be frightened now, you must accept!
Oh, Miss Shirley!
You've always been able to smooth things over with mama.
Please try to get her to forgive me?
Oh it's you is it?
Mrs. Harris please hear me through patiently...
I'm always patient... very patient.
| want you to know that Pauline is greatly troubled.
She is of the opinion that she should accept Isaac Kent's
hand in marriage.
| thought there was some foolishness between her
and that ridiculous fellow!
In your heart you must know it's the right thing to do.
The truth is, Pauline needs your forgiveness if she's
ever gonna be happy.
| advised her to be married.
And | beg of you to let her go.
If you've managed to get Pauline to accept that Isaac Kent
you've accomplished more than | thought was humanly possible.
At least | shan't have to climb down and tell him to take her.
"| withhold not my heart from any joy..."
That is Bible authority for you.
My dear, Man is born into trouble
as the sparks fly upwards...
Job 5 verse 6 Miss Shirley.
Pauline... come... here... girl!
No one can deny Margaret Pringle Harris' place as a cornerstone
of our community.
It is with great remorse that we turn her spirit
over to her master.
Though our hearts be troubled with this grave loss,
we must remind ourselves of the fleetingness of our own lives
and that some day we shall rejoice with Margaret forever
in the hereafter.
Amen.
Good-bye.
Thank you.
You're welcome.
We're going back to Boston, Miss Shirley.
Pauline has accepted Isaac Kent.
I've decided to sell Maplehurst.
How | shall miss you Em.
But we will see each other again soon.
And | promise you | won't ever forget you, just you mind that.
| will.
Good-bye Miss Shirley.
There's no one in the whole world like you.
Please accept my condolences Morgan.
Mother mentioned you before she went.
She was very keen on you.
She was never one to throw away a compliment.
That means a great deal to me.
Will you not reconsider?
I've come very close to reconsidering...
But it isn't any use Morgan.
I'll miss you, Anne.
| hope you rent that big old house on the Gulf someday,
'cause I'll miss you too.
| haven't had a chance to thank you Miss Brooke it's been such
a rewarding year.
Don't be ridiculous, please.
Where will you be spending your summer holidays?
Here in this fire-trap.
Where did you suppose?
Why stay if you don't like it?
Why... why?
Don't trouble yourself.
You've paid your lip service.
Now good-bye.
| shall see you next term.
| won't be coming back next term.
I've given my resignation to the board and Miss Stacey.
| came here to ask you if you'd like to spend your holidays
with me at Green Gables.
Unless you have somewhere else you're going.
An outburst of charity...
I'm hardly a candidate for that yet.
Katherine Brooke whether you know it or not what you want
iS a darn good spanking.
It must have relieved you to Say that.
It has.
And I've wanted to say it to you for a very long time.
But | have asked you to come because the very idea
of you spending the summer cooped up in here is indecent.
You asked me because you feel sorry for me.
| am sorry for you.
You shut out life and now life is shutting you out.
Now are you coming or not?
What would you say if | accepted?
I'd say that's the first faint glimmer of common sense
I've ever detected in you.
Alright | accept.
Now you can go through the motions of telling me how
delighted you are and how I'll have a wonderful time.
Lam delighted.
But as to a wonderful time that will depend entirely
on you Katherine.
The murder trials in this Boston paper my niece sent me
are real interesting Marilla.
Full of heathen, that place.
| hope Anne will never go there again.
Can you imagine that new minister going on about how he
doesn't believe that all the heathen will be eternally lost!
The idea!
If they won't be, all the money we've been sending to the.
Foreign Missions will be completely wasted, that's what!
| wouldn't fret if | were you Rachel.
Goodness knows the world is full of beggars and it's a pretty
pass if we can't help a fellow being in need, Christian or not.
Marilla Cuthbert!
Don't you be buying any junk from those peddlers just
to satisfy your conscience.
Oh it's an ill wind that blows no good.
Come back here you'll kill yourself running.
Oh, Marilla!
Anne Shirley!
I'm home Marilla.
I'm home to stay.
Oh you blessed child!
How I've missed you.
We were looking for you tomorrow.
How did you get from Bright River?
| walked, dearest of Marillas.
We left our luggage at the station.
| got homesick all at once and | wanted to show Katherine
all my old haunts.
Welcome to Green Gables.
Thank you for having me Miss Cuthbert.
Aren't these blossoms fragrant?
Smell them Marilla
drink them in.
Now enough of that nonsense.
It's you | want to hear about, not drinking in blossoms.
You must be real tired, Katherine.
Come and have a cup of tea on the verandah.
Oh, let's go slowly Marilla.
I've dreamt of this moment all year.
| want to soak it all in.
Not if Rachel has anything to do with it, she'll want to spill
out all the news of Avonlea.
Oh Anne Shirley.
I've got so much to tell you!
There's so much going on in Avonlea.
Oh Rachel, | have so much to tell you!
It's so good to see you again!
Rachel, this is Katherine Brooke.
Rachel Lynde.
How do you do?
Pleased to meet you.
Come on in now...
Green Gables never changes.
That's the beautiful thing about coming home, don't you think?
Katherine?
What's wrong?
Can | help you?
You can't understand!
Everything's always been so easy for you.
I'm caught in a trap.
|- | don't' think I'm ever going to be able to get out!
You don't hate me any longer, do you?
Oh Anne.
Hate has got to be like a disease with me!
| can never lead a normal life, now.
Yes you can!
You'll be quite independent and free here!
When | was a little girl, | remember an old faded print
on my uncle's wall showing a string of camels
around a desert with a palm spring.
I've always wanted to travel and see that place.
To see the Taj Mahal, the pillars at Carnet!
| want to know, not just believe,
that the world is round.
| could never do it on a teacher's salary.
| shall have to go on forever, prating about discipline
and the inexhaustible resources of the dominion!
| always wanted to be your friend, Katherine
spelled with a "K".
Underneath all your prickles, you really are a kindred spirit!
Does life never frighten you with its bleakness,
Anne Shirley?
This is the first place that I've ever been to that feels
like a real... home.
Isn't he perfect?
He is the most perfect baby I've ever seen, Diana.
Every baby is the sweetest and the best.
Before he came! Wanted a girl so | could call her Anne.
But | wouldn't exchange baby Fred for a million girls.
If you had an Anne you'd feel the same about her.
Would you like to hold the baby Katherine?
No, no... I've never held a baby in my life.
Never held a baby!
Don't be silly.
I'm afraid of it going to pieces in my arms.
There you are, he's taken with you Katherine.
It feels so good to see you dear folk again.
| want to hear all the Avonlea news.
I've grown a whole inch since you left Anne.
And now that squirt Anthony Pye can't pick on me anymore.
Can't you think of any more interesting news
than that Minnie May!
Did you know that Gilbert Blythe was dying?
Minnie May hold your tongue!
What do you mean Diana?
We didn't mean to tell you so suddenly, Anne.
He took scarlet fever in mid-term.
He picked it up at the hospital in Halifax.
Terrible worn out with school | expect.
They got a trained nurse and everything's been done.
| picked this up at the Post Office.
It's addressed to you.
My... my book!
Well don't sit there shaking like a leaf!
Open it.
Oh Marilla.
This can't be real.
They accepted my manuscript last February with a $250 advance.
You're a great one for secrets.
It's not a classic ora romance or anything important.
Just a humorous book of stories | did about Avonlea
in my spare time last fall.
But it's mine, it's all mine.
"To Marilla and Matthew Cuthbert for their unfailing love and
support and for Gilbert who inspired me with the idea
in the first place.'.
You do beat all Anne.
Everyone'll think | put you up to it.
That's awful good of you; Especially considering Gilbert.
How sick is he really?
It's been a bad case from the start.
No one's heard anything the past week.
He has the Blythe constitution
in his favour though... if God wills it.
Marilla there's a Book of Revelations in everyone's life.
I've been so wrong.. If Gil were to
not knowing how | really care.
Oh, there there now.
What would | do without him?
We can't change what God determines.
Jerry Boote... Jerry Boote works for Mr. Blythe.
It must be a sign.
The worst would be more endurable
than not knowing at all.
Jerry! Jerry!
Jerry, wait!
Jerry do you know how Gilbert Blythe is doing?
| think, | think he's bad.
The Blythes are all hoping he's gonna get better.
| don't know.
The doctor figures maybe
he's gonna have a close shave yet, though.
Will you ask Mr. Blythe to give him this for me?
Come with me if you like and give it to him yourself.
Hello Gil.
It's me.
Anne.
I've come to ask you to go for one of our old-time
rambles in the woods.
Wish | could go.
| brought you my book.
I've been published Gil.
| wrote about Avonlea just as you said | should.
Without any "high faulting mumbo jumbo".
I've dedicated the inscription to Marilla
and to Matthew, and... to you.
| was planning on saving itas a wedding gift, and then
| just decided | couldn't wait.
Anne, there's not going to be any wedding, anymore.
You're gonna well again Gil. | know you will.
| called it off.
It wouldn't be fair to Christine.
Oh Gil...
There would never be anyone for me but you.
Oh, Anne, the summer's flown by so quickly.
A schoolteacher really is a Slave of time.
| don't know how I'm ever going to go back.
Don't be silly.
There's always another bend in the road.
Bend in the road.
There's no bend in my road.
| can see it stretching out in front of me to the skyline.
Katherine, just look at you.
You're rosy and healthy.
And you hair looks so attractive like that
instead of all pulled back.
Besides, | happen to know of two eligible young men
who've asked about you.
Really?
They're gonna be at the bonfire tonight.
Oh, | wouldn't know what to say to them.
Will you help me, Anne?
They'll just laugh at me and think I'm an old gooseberry.
You give yourself far too little credit.
| wish | had your confidence.
| can believe almost anything of this Green Gables of yours.
Well, mine's full.
I'll be along.
| want to make sure Marilla has three full bushels.
Hello Anne.
Hello Gil.
You're looking very robust.
Well, I... uh... 1 guess | just made up my mind
| wasn't going to let it lick me.
Care for a stroll down the lane.
| don't think there's going to be many more fine afternoons
like this left in the summer.
| wish | could, but...
Katherine and I, we're off to Alice Penhallow's bonfire
in an hour.
It's the first party I'm taking her to and she's very nervous.
How about | walk you across the pond.
| was really afraid for you Gil, until we heard you
were over the worst.
Well | was lucky | suppose.
I'm not quite my old self yet.
By the time term Starts I'll be in fine form.
I'm glad you came back when you did Anne.
It meant a lot to me.
| finally read your book.
It's a fine piece of work.
| knew you could do it.
The Publishers are already planning a second edition.
It was along lesson to learn, but you were right.
I'm not going back to Kingsport.
I'm gonna stay here at Green Gables and write.
Private girls' school was too rough on you, was it?
No.
It's just that | went looking for my ideals outside of myself.
I've discovered it's not what the world holds for you,
it's what you bring to it.
The dreams dearest to my heart are right here.
Well | hope you keep on dreaming.
It'll be three years before | finish medical school.
Even then there won't be any diamond sunbursts
or marble halls.
| don't want sunbursts or marble halls.
| just want you.